<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning the excommunication of the Venetians a discourse against Cæsar Baronius Cardinall of the Church of Rome In which the true nature and vse of excommunication is briefly and cleerly demonstrated, both by testimonies of Holy Scripture, and from the old records of Christs Church. Written in Latine by Nicolas Vignier, and translated into English after the copie printed at Samur 1606. Whereunto is added the Bull of Pope Paulus the Fift, against the Duke, Senate and Commonwealth of Venice: with the protestation of the sayd Duke and Senate. As also an apologie of Frier Paul of the order of Serui in Venice.</title>
            <title>De Venetorum excommunicatione, adversus Caesarem Baronium. English</title>
            <author>Vignier, Nicolas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14399</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21485</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14399)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21485)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning the excommunication of the Venetians a discourse against Cæsar Baronius Cardinall of the Church of Rome In which the true nature and vse of excommunication is briefly and cleerly demonstrated, both by testimonies of Holy Scripture, and from the old records of Christs Church. Written in Latine by Nicolas Vignier, and translated into English after the copie printed at Samur 1606. Whereunto is added the Bull of Pope Paulus the Fift, against the Duke, Senate and Commonwealth of Venice: with the protestation of the sayd Duke and Senate. As also an apologie of Frier Paul of the order of Serui in Venice.</title>
                  <title>De Venetorum excommunicatione, adversus Caesarem Baronium. English</title>
                  <author>Vignier, Nicolas.</author>
                  <author>Sarpi, Paolo, 1552-1623. Apologia per le oppositioni fatte dall'illustrissimo &amp; reverendissimo signor cardinale Bellarminio alli trattati, et risolutioni di Gio. Gersone. English.</author>
                  <author>Baronio, Cesare, 1538-1607. Duo vota. English.</author>
                  <author>Catholic Church. Pope (1605-1621 : Paul V)</author>
                  <author>Venice (Republic : to 1797). Doge (1606-1612 : Donato)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 49, [1], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[elchisidec] B[radwood] for C[uthbert] B[urby] and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the White-swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: De Venetorum excommunicatione, adversus Caesarem Baronium.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation of and reply to: Baronio, Cesare. Duo vota.</note>
                  <note>"The bull of Pope Paulus the Fift, against the common wealth and Senate of Venice" (caption title) begins new pagination on G3r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paul --  V, --  Pope, 1552-1621 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baronio, Cesare, 1538-1607. --  Duo vota --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  History --  Papal Interdict, 1606-1607 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Concerning the Excommunication of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians <hi>A DISCOVRSE Againſt CAESAR BARONIVS Cardinall of the Church of ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which the true nature and vſe of Excommunication is briefly and cleerly demonſtrated, both by Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Holy Scripture, and from the old Records of Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in Latine by NICOLAS VIGNIER, and tranſlated into Engliſh after the Copie printed at</hi> Samur <hi>1606.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is added the Bull of Pope PAVLVS the</hi> Fift, againſt the Duke, Senate and Commonwealth <hi>of VENICE: With the proteſtation of</hi> the ſayd Duke and Senate.</p>
            <p>As alſo an Apologie of Frier <hi>PAVL</hi> of the <hi>Order of</hi> Serus <hi>in VENICE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>M. B.</hi> for <hi>C. B.</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls <hi>Church-yard at the ſigne of the White-ſwan. 1607.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="advice">
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21485:2"/>
            <head>CAESAR BARONIVS his aduice vnto Pope PAVL <hi>the Fift, to excommunicate the</hi> Venetians.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eters</hi> office <hi>(Holy Father)</hi> is twofold; To <hi>Feed</hi> and to <hi>Kill:</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid vnto him<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.15.</note> 
               <hi>Feede my ſheepe:</hi> and he heard a voice from heauen,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>Kill and Eat.</hi> To <hi>Feede</hi> the <hi>ſheepe,</hi> is with care to watch ouer the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obedient Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, reſembling <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Lambes</hi> in all humility and religious piety. When he hath to do, not with <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Lambes,</hi> but <hi>Lions</hi> and like beaſts of fierce natures, refractary, ſtubborne, and diſobedient, then <hi>Peter</hi> hath charge to <hi>Kill:</hi> that is, to reſiſt, fight againſt and root out ſuch: and that ſuch <hi>killing</hi> ſhould euer be in <hi>Charity,</hi> he is willed to <hi>Eat</hi> that which he had ſlaine in effect, through that <hi>Loue</hi> which he beares to them in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to lay them vp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, euen in his owne bowels, that <hi>In Chriſt we may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21485:3"/>be</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.28.</note> 
               <hi>one,</hi> which is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> owne ſaying:<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>I long after you in the bowels of Chriſt.</hi> And ſo, this <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> is not <hi>Cruelty</hi> but <hi>Piety</hi> and ſyncere <hi>Charity:</hi> When, ſo by <hi>killing,</hi> he <hi>ſaueth</hi> that which by being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo to liue, had otherwiſe <hi>periſhed</hi> for euer. And therefore, as <hi>Pope Nicolas</hi> the firſt ſheweth, <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication is not a poiſon to kill, but rather a</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Potion</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to recure.</hi> And we ſee, that a <hi>Father</hi> thinks well of thoſe bands wherewith the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> hath bound his franticke ſonne, becauſe he hopeth it will doe him good. Go on then, on <hi>Gods</hi> name, moſt holy <hi>Father</hi> in your courſe begun, and ſuppoſe not that any man can iuſtly tax your too great haſtines in theſe proceedings. That which <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath written to his brethren<note n="f" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 6.</note> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that the <hi>Church is ready to reuenge all diſobedience,</hi> is a <hi>Command,</hi> that the Church ſhould bee forward to do it. Your <hi>Holineſſe</hi> happily hath beene too backward, as yet not proceeding farther then to write. For my owne part, I profeſſe I am glad and reioice in my ſpirit, nay I will ſay with the Apoſtle, I do<note n="g" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ouer-abound in ioy,</hi> ſeeing I ſee now, in my<note n="h" place="margin">The man is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout 68. years old. <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. <hi>Hilachrand. Alexander</hi> 3. <hi>Vide Plat.</hi>
               </note> decrepit age, to ſit on <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſeat, <hi>Gregory</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> (the firſt two liuely roots from whence the dead <hi>Church-liberty</hi> began to reuiue) both called from <hi>Siena,</hi> (the place from whence<note n="i" place="margin">Being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before his Papacy Camillo Borgheſe of Siena.</note> your Holineſſe is extract) to the <hi>Chaire of Peter.</hi> Of which two, the one gat the better of the Emperour<note n="k" place="margin">Henry the 4.</note> 
               <hi>Henry,</hi> a moſt wilfull and peruerſe man, and the other by his incredible ſtrange conſtancy vtterly vanquiſhed<note n="l" place="margin">Frederick Barboroſ<hi rend="sup">s</hi>;a.</note> 
               <hi>Frederick.</hi> Your <hi>Holineſſe</hi> hath the like cauſe now in hand. In your hands (to borow the<note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets</hi> words) theſe ruines lie to reedifie the <hi>Liberty of the Church</hi> fallen downe, deiected, and laid low on the Earth. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21485:3"/>with <hi>victory</hi> that attends you. For <hi>God</hi> is with vs,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>The gates of hell</hi> (they be <hi>Chriſts</hi> wordes) <hi>ſhall not preuaile againſt you.</hi> You are placed in the <hi>Church Peters ſucceſſor,</hi> and haue the promiſe, made to him. <hi>Let corne be giuen them out of the rocke,</hi> and as it is in the Prophecy of Ieremy, <hi>I haue made thee a</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.28.</note> 
               <hi>piller of iron and a wall of braſſe.</hi> Remember, you are placed as<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 8</note> 
               <hi>a rocke in the Church, on which all that ſtumble ſhall be daſhed in pieces.</hi> But you ſhall continue without hurt, ioined cloſe and vnited vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſhall fight for you &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:4"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21485:4"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER OF NICOLAS VIGNIER vnto <hi>Caeſar Baronius.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nicolaus de Clamengis libro de ruina &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione ecclae.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an ancient ſpeech vſed by one, who was not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of <hi>Rome;</hi> That were a Painter deſirous to draw the picture of Pride, his beſt courſe were to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a Cardinall. If a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man, and inwardly familiar with ſome Popes themſelues, had iuſt cauſe thus to write two hundred yeeres ſince, how much more iuſtly doth it ſute theſe times, in which they want, neither high-ſwelling wordes, nor deteſtable impieties, to effect and bring about their wicked deſignes? Very lately there flew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the world, a certaine writing from Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Baronius, concerning the excommunicating the State of Venice, directed vnto Pope Paul the fift. In which the truth is ſo cleerly euidenced, that though a man would deny the Sunne to ſhine at noone, yet could hee not at all deny it. So liuely and in ſuch a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21485:5"/>plain ſort doth the man paint out himſelfe &amp; his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, that in them you would ſweare you ſaw Pride herſelfe. What leaueth he vndone or vnattempted, to ſet vp his Iuppiter Capitoline, an Idoll to be ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the place of Chriſt? And what, I pray you, be his meanes? Surely the ſame and no other whereby that Angell of darkneſſe deceiueth the ſimple, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting himſelfe an <hi>Angell of light.</hi> For ſo crafty is that blood-ſucker Sathan, that he neuer appeareth in his natiue ſhape, but putteth on the perſon of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So he aſſaied and deceiued Saul,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.14.</note> in apparition of graue and holy Samuel. So ſeduced he Abab, by the mouth of his Prophets.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.22.</note> So he drowned many of the Iewes in the Sea, taking vpon him to lead them in the likeneſſe of Moſes. So in like ſort at this day he exciteth and eggeth forward Paul the fift, chiefe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop on earth, Vicar of Chriſt, Succeſſor of Peter, Prince of Prelates, King of Kings, Lord of Lords, Father of Fathers, head of the Church, the eſſentiall forme of Iuſtice, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the Chriſt of God, as they inſtile him, to commit murthers, wage warres, become an Incendiarie, be the ſubuertor and ruiner of the ſtate of Venice, the moſt noble and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Common-wealth of the world, and that in the perſon of a reuerend old man clad in ſcarlet robes, a Cardinall of marke, famous for learning, pretending nothing but alone the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peters</hi> office (as you ſay <hi>Holy Father</hi>) is twofold, to <hi>Feed,</hi> and to <hi>Kill: Diuinitie</hi> not drempt of by our Predeceſſors. <hi>Peters</hi> office is to <hi>Feed,</hi> and to <hi>Kill.</hi> By what right? by what authoritie? Certes Chriſt did conſtitute his Apoſtles, Paſtors, to feed that Church
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21485:5"/>which himſelfe had acquired by his blood, which alſo is the dutie of all and euerie one which haue any charge in the church, wherunto <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe giues witneſſe, when hee ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>The Elders which are among you I beſeech, which am alſo an Elder</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Feed the flocke of God which dependeth vpon you, caring for it, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; not as though you were Lords ouer the heritage of God, but that you may be enſamples vnto the flocke: and when the chiefe ſheepheard ſhall appeare,</hi> (not that Arch Flamn of Rome, but Chriſt) <hi>you ſhall receiue an incorruptible crowne of glorie.</hi> But as for that office of <hi>Killing,</hi> not any the leaſt mention in the booke of God, vnleſſe it may be in theſe places, where ſuch Paſtors be deciphered, as in conditions reſemble your ſcarlet Colledge ſo well, that milke cannot be more like to milke than you to them. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom we read that God of old ſpake in this ſort vnto Ezechiel:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech</hi> 34.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God vnto the ſhepheards, Woe vnto the ſhepheards of Iſrael that feed themſelues. Should not the ſhepheards feed the flocks? You eat the milke and cloath yourſelues with the fat, you kill the beſt, but feed not my flocke. The weake haue you not ſtrengthened, the ſicke haue you not healed, neither haue you bound vp the broken, nor brought that againe which was driuen away, neither haue you ſought that which was loſt, but with cruelty and with rigour haue you ruled them. And they were ſcattered without a ſhepheard</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore ô ſhepheards heare the word of Iehoua. Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold I am againſt the ſhepheards, and will require my ſheep at their hands; and cauſe them to ceaſe from feeding the flocke, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21485:6"/>theſe ſhepheards may no longer feed themſelues: for I will deliuer my ſheepe from their mouthes and they ſhall no more deuoure them.</hi> Which <hi>Prophecy</hi> you ſee is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in your ſelues, that haue loſt England, Sweland Denmarke; Norway and the greater part of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deliuered from your deuouring mouthes, and you can no more obtrude your merchandiſe vpon them, your <hi>Lambes of wax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agnos Dei.</note> your <hi>hallowed beades,</hi> your <hi>Bulles,</hi> your <hi>Iubiles.</hi> But come wee to the grounds whereon this paradox is built, and to thoſe pillars that beare it vp.<note place="margin">B</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto him, Feed my ſheep;</hi> and <hi>he heard a voice from Heauen, Kill and Eat.</hi> I maruel you deduce not your office of <hi>killing,</hi> out of the firſt word,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Rom. Pontifice c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Feed, ſeeing Bellarmine not the leaſt among theſe ſcarlet Worthies hath found your Popes Regall authoritie therein. For Homer (ſaith the man) in his ſecond Ilias (from whom Chriſt no doubt did bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row this phraſe) calleth Agamemnon once and again Paſtor of the people,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who (it is certaine) ſlew and ſent many packing away to Pluto, and therefore ſhared it ſhould ſeeme this office of killing with you. But paſſe wee from theſe bables, and come vnto the oracles more renowmed than the <hi>Delphian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter heard a voice from heauen, Kill and eat.</hi> What if he did?<note place="margin">B <hi>Matth.</hi> 26 52. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.13.</note> He heard alſo from * Chriſts own mouth, <hi>Put vp thy ſword into thy ſheath; for he that ſtriketh with the ſword ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi> Whether voice of the two, did moſt amate Peter? that which bid him, or that which did forbid him to <hi>kill?</hi> Either was this his voice vttered by him whom it is high impiety to diſobey, whom all religion tieth to yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto, who cannot lie, nor cannot deceiue. And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21485:6"/>Peter was obedient vnto both. He did not caſt away the keies, which Chriſt had committed to him ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the other * Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 16.19.</note> and take him vnto his ſword, as * one of the Popes of Rome is reported to haue caſt Peters keies into the Tiber, and laid hold,<note place="margin">Pope Iulv the ſecond that Butifeu of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly.</note> as he called it, vpon Pauls ſwords; but ſubiected himſelfe vnto Neroes ſword; and as well by example taught others ſo to do, as by this his expreſſe precept:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues vnto all maner ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be vnto the King, as vnto the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioror, vnto gouernours, as vnto them that are ſent of him for the puniſhment of euill doers and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> Neither hauing receiued that meſſage <hi>Kill and eat,</hi> did he withdraw himſelfe from the ſociety of the Gentiles, which was the ſcope and end both of this voice and heauenly viſion. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant as then, that the ceremonies of Moſes law were to be aboliſhed, and the Gentiles to be ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated into the people of God, without receiuing the ſeale of circumciſion, or obſeruing of other legall rites, Chriſt by this viſion would teach him the truth: for that <hi>ſheet</hi> and <hi>veſſell</hi> which Peter beheld, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the Church of Chriſt, which is ſaid to be let down from heauen, becauſe it is on Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence more ſtrongly ſuſpended than if it were faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto Iupiters golden chaine, wherof Homer ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. There be within the continent of the Church, liuing creatures of euery kind vnder heauen: foure-footed, flying, creeping things, cleane and vncleane (that is to ſay, which as yet Peter did not know) Iewes and Gentile. <hi>That is, the myſtery which in former times was not diſcloſed vnto men, but now is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21485:7"/>to his Apoſtles and Prophets in the Spirit: that the Gentiles are to be made one body coheires and copartners of the promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpell,</hi> as Paul ſpeaketh Eph. 3. Which viſion becauſe of ſome obſcurity in it, is farther illuſtrated in courſe of Scripture: <hi>Kill,</hi> ſaith he, and <hi>Eat,</hi> without difference, cleane and vncleane beaſts.<note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>11.</hi> per totum.</note> For howſoeuer it was hitherto by the law for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, it is now permitted by grace in Chriſt: which to be the intendment and ſcope of that viſion, Peter himſelfe doth conteſt in theſe words of his vnto Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius: <hi>You know it is vnlawfull for a man that is a Iew to company or conuerſe with one of another nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>But God hath ſhewed me, that I muſt not call any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed or impure.</hi> And this is the generall expoſition of the Fathers, agreeing thereupon with one conſent, out of whoſe Commentings and large enarrations <hi>Oecumenius</hi> collected thoſe his ſummary notes which hee hath left vpon the Acts of the Apoſtles. His words be theſe:<note place="margin">Oecumenius in Act. Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rum.</note> 
               <hi>The veſſell which he ſaw deſigneth the world made of groſſe ſubſtance. The beaſts of diuers kinds are types of the different degrees of man. And to ſpeake more plainly. The ſheet is the Church. The liuing creatures in it be the Gentiles. Peter ſaw the Church tied and knit vnto the foure Euangeliſts, and all nations contained therein. It was ſaid vnto him, Kill and Eat, becauſe it was neceſſary that euen they ſhould come vnto the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is heere, <hi>Baronius,</hi> that concerneth that Office of killing? By this voice, and this viſion Peter is commanded to go vnto the Gentiles and feed them with the holeſome and liuely food of the Goſpell. This is with you to kill and ſlay. And happily for this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21485:7"/>cauſe you take that good courſe, not to preach the Goſpell, leſt thereby you might become murtherers, or rather indeed, leſt the people hating the poiſon of your traditions do hunger after the bread of life. But this is your maner to interpret Scriptures, vpon which you ſtand ſo much, which you learned of the great profeſſor of your ſchoole and Doctor of the chaire, he I meane who in the deſert, detorted and wreſted (as you are wont to do) the Scriptures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.</note> in his diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with our Sauiour. Such one was <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. (of whom the ſaying goeth, <hi>He entred as a fox,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Maior. &amp; obedien. Vnam ſanctam.</note> 
               <hi>raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a lion, and died as a dog</hi>) who would proue that the Pope had right to both the ſwords Spirituall and Temporal, out of the Euangelicall writings forſooth. Becauſe when the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>Here are two ſwords,</hi> the Lord did not anſwer his Apoſtles, (ſpeaking in the Church (Heere) it <hi>is too much,</hi> but <hi>it is inough.</hi> Certainly, whoſoeuer ſhall denie that the temporall ſword is in the power of Peter, he regardeth but little Gods word, which ſaith: <hi>Put vp thy ſword into thy ſheath.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>1.16.</hi> De Maiorit. &amp; Obed. C. ſolitae.</note> And Innocent the 3. by a place of Geneſis doth as ſoundly proue that the Imperiall maieſtie is in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to the Pontificall. <hi>You ſhould</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>haue conſidered that God made two great lights in the firmament of Heauen, the greater light to rule the day, the ſmaller light to gouern the night, both great, but one greater than the other. In the firmament of heauen, that is, the vniuerſal Church, God made two great lights, that is, appointed two eſtates royall, the Pontificall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Regall power, but that is the greater of the twain which is appointed ouer the day, that is, ouer ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, that the leſſe which hath iuriſdiction in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21485:8"/>that wee may know there is as great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Kings and Popes as there is betwixt the Sunne and Moone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>22.</hi> ſacroſancta.</note> In like ſort Anacletus, if * Gratian ſay true, proued the Primacie of Saint Peter out of that place where hee is called Cephas, that is, an Head and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which Etymologie euen * Bellarmine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudeth,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Roma. Pontif. c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> who affirmeth that Cephas is an head in Greeke,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whereas Cephas is not a Greeke but a Syriak word, which as himſelfe auerreth, ſignifies a Rocke. And the ſame Bellarmine that Captain Ieſuite, out of the ſelfe ſame place which you produce, <hi>Kill and Eat,</hi> concludeth that Peter is Head of the Church, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his argument, not as you do from the word <hi>Kill,</hi> but from the Commandement <hi>Eat.</hi> For ſaith he, <hi>It is the heads duty to eate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bella. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Rom. Pontific. c. <hi>22.</hi> Barom. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Annal. Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo by eating to tranſmit the meat into the ſtomack, and ſo to incorporate it to it ſelfe.</hi> And your * ſelfe elſewhere do bring this proofe to make the vſe of <hi>ſhrining</hi> the reliques of Saints within the Altars, Apoſtolicall, becauſe in the ſixt chapter of the Reuelation, <hi>the ſoules</hi> of ſuch as were ſlaine for the Goſpell, are ſaid <hi>to cry from vnder the Altar.</hi> But who is not acquainted with ſuch Iuglers trickes? what man will take their counterfeit glaſſe for true pearle? Remember Baronius, that I may returne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelf an allegory, that the Chamelion a beaſt, which (as they ſay) liueth by the aire is numbred with ſuch * as be vncleane;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 11. Alluſion to the ſpeech that Emperor. <hi>Fumum habet qui fumum vendidit.</hi> B</note> and that vaine man, blowen vp with wind, who <hi>ſelleth nothing but ſmoke</hi> is ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably vncleane in the eyes of God. But to proceed: <hi>To feede the ſheepe is with care to watch ouer the faithfull</hi> &amp;c. And is it true indeed, Baronius, is the office of feeding to be confined only to the faithfull
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21485:8"/>and obedient Chriſtians, and is this your will to haue all refractarie and ſtubborn ones led into the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whom happily you inſtile Lions, for that you feare the Lion the <hi>armes of Venice?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 11.6.</note> But Eſay prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied otherwiſe of Chriſts Kingdome. <hi>The Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lie with the Kid; and the Calfe, and the Lion, and the fat beaſt together, and a little child ſhall lead them. The Cow and the Beare ſhall feed, their yoong ones ſhall lie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Lion ſhall eat ſtraw like the Bullocke, the ſucking child ſhall play vpon the hole of the Aſpe, and the weined child ſhall thruſt his hand into the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice hole. Then none ſhall hurt nor deſtroy in all the mountaine of mine holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee deny not but Paſtors are to ſtand againſt the refractarie and the diſobedient, but with what armes? Spirituall not Carnall. For as Hierome once ſayd of hereſie:<note place="margin">Ieron. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>4.</hi> in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiam.</note> 
               <hi>Hereſie is to be cut off with the ſword of the Spirit; let vs ſtrike thorow with the arrowes of the Spirit, all ſons and diſciples of miſled Heretiques, that is, with Teſtimonies of holy Scripture. The ſlaughter of Heretiks is by the word of God.</hi> So wee ſay and iudge of all other vices. For the Church hath no ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as to vſe the ſword of the Ciuill Magiſtrate, or bring in within her liberties politicke puniſhments, the offices of the Ciuill and Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtrate being, as Chriſt teacheth <hi>Matt.</hi> 20. things of diuers natures: <hi>You know, That kings of Nations rule ouer them, but with you it ſhall not be ſo.</hi> And the reaſon is, for that the Church is the ſeruant of Chriſt no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then as Chriſt is the Sauiour of the faithfull: But Chriſt to procure the ſaluation of them, neuer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21485:9"/>vſed himſelfe, nor permitted his Church to vſe, the ſword of the ciuill Magiſtrate. And this is that, if I miſtake not, which your ſelfe in proſecution of your allegories adde, <hi>That ſuch killing muſt not be but with great charitie</hi> &amp;c. For all that we do or can conclude from hence, is this and no more, that this killing of the ſtubborn and diſobedient is done by Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>which is a ſpirituall and wholeſome remedie.</hi> Which to grant, wee muſt firſt conſider, leſt we erre in ambiguitie of wordes, <hi>What excommunication is,</hi> 2. <hi>By whom it may be executed.</hi> 3. <hi>Vpon whom to be inflicted.</hi> 4. <hi>For what cauſes it is iuſt.</hi> 5. <hi>From what communion they bee barred.</hi> 6. <hi>Which bee the ends of Excommunication:</hi> that any man by theſe grounds may determine what is to be iudged of the Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the State of Venice, of which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Excommunication,</hi> one of the parts of Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, the other being brotherly Correction, is of two kindes; The <hi>Leſſer</hi> and the <hi>Greater: The Leſſe is that whereby ſuch as grieuouſly offend againſt any point of faith, or maners, or good eſtabliſhed order, are excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate;</hi> not ſo that abſolutely they ceaſe to bee the members of Chriſt, but be only for a time reſtrained from communion of the Sacraments, ſo long as, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till either their <hi>Repentance,</hi> or <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Dutie</hi> bee iudged ſufficient, and publick ſcandall be taken away. And ſuch the * <hi>Ancients</hi> called <hi>Reſtrained.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abſtenti. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. in epiſtolis.</note> 
               <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication the Greater, is an holy action of Prieſthood, by which, agreably to the rule of Chriſt, a brother become obſtinate in his ſins, is cut off from the fellowſhip of the faithfull, caſt out of the Church, deliuered to Sathan,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21485:9"/>that vpon correction he may repent, and vpon true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be againe receiued,</hi> which was vnder the law, a caſting forth out from the Synagogue.</p>
            <p>So by authoritie and warrant of Chriſt, <hi>to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate is a power belonging vnto all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>and none but the True Church:</hi> to be executed by the whole Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie lawfully elected, to bee denounced in the open face of the aſſembly, with their either tacit or expreſſe conſent. This is proued by the words of Chriſt, <hi>If he will not heare the Church,</hi> that is, the Presbytery and conuention of Elders, <hi>let him be to thee as an Ethnicke &amp; a Publicane.</hi> The Apoſtle is yet more cleare in this point 1. Cor. 5. <hi>When you are gathered together, and my ſpirit in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; let ſuch a one be deliuered vnto Sathan.</hi> In which place he ſpeaketh vnto the whole Church as again he doth 2. Cor. 2. <hi>It is ſufficient that this man hath beene cenſured by many.</hi> And therfore he intreateth that with one conſent they receiue againe him who had beene excommunicate. And this is the doctrine and * conſent of all fathers,<note place="margin">What, This if he meane by the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it. The Church practiſe &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the fathers is to the contrary.</note> as in Cyprians epiſtles any man may read. Wherof the reaſon is very euident, that matters of greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence in the church are not to be proceeded in without conſent and approbation of the<note n="*" place="margin">Either tacite or expreſſe as before.</note> whole Church, as the practiſe is in ciuill ſtates and affaires. For <hi>that wherein euerie one is intereſſed,</hi> (it was the ſaying of Pope Leo) <hi>muſt haue the generall conſent of all.</hi> And what of more conſequence? wherein can the whole bodie be more intereſſed, than in the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of one member from the bodie? The concluſion therefore is: <hi>No man ought to bee excommunicate, without the generall aſſent of the whole Church in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21485:10"/>which he liueth.</hi> And that Auſten was of this minde, it is euident by this, that he thinketh that man ſhould not be excommunicated, who hath many abetters and bearers out in his offence, with whom many do partake and are aſſociate in ſinne, reioycing in their follies, inſulting on the godly, deſpiſing the ſword of Excommunication, leſt it proue the originall of a Schiſme; and of this mind, ſaith he, the Apoſtle was. His wordes are: <hi>To this purpoſe the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: If any one be named:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Contra epiſtolam Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In that he ſaith: If any one, it ſeemeth his meaning was that ſuch a man might ſafely be put vnder cenſure, and for his good, who is a ſinner among ſuch as be none, that is, as be not infected with the taint of like enormity. And where he ſaith, be named hee letteth vs therby vnderſtand it is not inough that a man be ſo, vnleſſe withall he be named to be ſo, that is, notoriouſly knowen and diffamed, that all men may prooue and giue their conſent to the ſentence of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication throwen foorth againſt him. For thus the bond of peace may bee kept, correction bee done vpon him, he be ſtriken, not to kill him, be ſeared, but to cure him. To this end hee ſaith of that man whom by ſuch receit hee would haue to bee cured: The Rebuke of many is ſufficient for him. Becauſe ſuch rebuke cannot be auaileable, but where one is rebuked, who hath not a multitude, his fellowes in ſinne: but if the infection be gone ouer many, the godly can do nothing but ſorrow and grieue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the perſons liable to this cenſure, <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>Only</hi> they, who being in the liſt of brethren, continue in ſin with contumacy. Only brethren, becauſe that, <hi>Of forreiners God doth iudge, and not the Church,</hi> as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21485:10"/>the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and ſuch as neuer had any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miunion, cannot be cut off from commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church which they neuer had. Again, adde the <hi>ſtubbornly wilfull,</hi> not others <hi>for them,</hi> or <hi>with them.</hi> Becauſe <hi>euery man muſt beare his owne burthen.</hi> And Auſten doth in this point deſeruedly blame Auxilius a yong man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 75. If by his own iudgement &amp; allegation out of Auſten for peril of ſchiſm excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation muſt not bee infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: if for nothing elſe, yet in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of greate ones, gods on earth ſhould not ſo eaſilie haue paſſed his lippes. Azarias did not excommunicate Vſziah, but told him his duty, as the miniſter of God. Neither did they compell him to haſten out, but God did it; and had they done it, this was no excommunication. 2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 26. <hi>Theodoret. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. ca.</hi> 18. S. Ambroſe is the only example that can with probability be alleadged. But there is very much difference betweene his maner of proceeding and the Popes in his conſiſtory, and the Miniſters with their elders. Read the ſtory in Theodoret. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. ca.</hi> 17. <hi>ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpr. Chriſtophorſani.</hi>
               </note> and ſomewhat elderly Biſhop, as he ſpeaketh, becauſe that for the ſole of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Claſſianus, he did excommunicate his whole family. And it is againſt All, that No man of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſtate or condition, Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill, Superior or Inferior, may thinke himſelfe exempted from that cenſure. The truth hereof is certaine by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in Scripture, as for inſtance. Azarias the high Prieſt caſt foorth king Ozias out of the Temple: by practiſe, in the prime age of the Chriſtian Church, when as Ambroſe excommunicated Theodoſius: an act allowed of by all Churches, and ſo well liked by Theodoſius himſelfe, that he profeſſed to haue met with but one Biſhop in deed, Ambroſe, at Millane.</p>
            <p>The cauſes which procure it, are ſins of Commiſſion, done without amendment, againſt either Firſt or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table. That appeareth by Chriſt his words <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. where he mentioneth Ethnicks, Tranſgreſſors of the <hi>Firſt;</hi> and then Publicanes, delinquents againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21485:11"/>the <hi>Second table.</hi> To which there in the 12. of Exodus, where there is charge giuen, that no <hi>Vncircumciſed perſon,</hi> and in that, an offendor againſt the firſt Table, be admitted to the <hi>Paſſeouer:</hi> and ſecondly,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</note> no Iew who had Leuen in his houſe, which leauen the Apoſtle doth interpret, of <hi>mal tiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vncleane life.</hi> Where he ſaith. <hi>Therfore let vs keepe the feaſt, not in the leauen of malice and iniquity, but with the vnleauened loues of ſyncerity and truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The communion is twofold wherefrom the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate are excluded, Internall, Externall. The Inward is that, by which euery faithfull man, in faith and charity is firſt knit vnto God, then to all the Saints and the whole body of the Church, with the bond of the ſpirit, which is in the Creed called the Communion of Saints, of which that place of Iohn is meant, 1. Ioh. 1. <hi>That which wee haueſeene, that which wee haue heard, do wee preach vnto you, that you</hi> (the faithfull) <hi>might haue communion with vs: and that our communion might bee with the Father, and with his ſonne Chriſt Ieſu.</hi> From this communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is not the Excommunication of the Presbytery, but their owne ſinnes which excludeth offendours. For the Prophet, as the <hi>mouth of God</hi> ſaith, <hi>Your ſinnes haue diuided me and you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.</note> But Excommunication doth declare, and confirme by the <hi>Churches authority,</hi> that the irrepentant ſinner is <hi>excluded</hi> and <hi>cut off from this communion.</hi> The ſaying of the Schoole to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, <hi>The Church doth not damnifie any man, but pointeth him out that is damnified.</hi> Euen as, when in the Law, the Prieſt did forbid the infected with the leproſie to enter within the Congregation. This
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21485:11"/>act of the Prieſt, did not bring the ſore vpon him, but only declared that he was infected: and hence it is, the <hi>if the key go not right,</hi> as the ſaying is, <hi>but hit vpon ſuch as be innocent, the ſentence pronounced is void.</hi> Externall communion is of two kindes, either in Church or Common wealth. This latter concerneth negotiating, trading and commerce in matters of ciuill courſe belonging vnto this preſent life. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication doth not actually depriue a man from the benefit of this, but it remaines lawfull for any, in ciuill affaires, to negotiate with him, to doe him all duties and bounden offices, ſuch as the ſonne ſhould do the father, the wife her husband, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects their magiſtrate: for euen to Ethnickes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans ſuch natural ſeruices be returnable. Eccleſiaſtical communion is that, wherein we communicate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thoſe things which in the Church of God concerne his ſeruice, as publicke praier, preaching of the Word, participation of the Sacraments. This laſt is cleerly and wholly forbidden the Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, both vpon warrant of Chriſt his precept,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>Giue not holy things vnto dogges. Caſt not pearles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwine:</hi> as alſo in regard of their fruit and effects: leſt happily they turne vnto their condemnation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>receiue vnworthily,</hi> it being the nature of the Sacrament to profit onely the worthy receiuer. Concerning the preaching of the word, although the vnfaithfull and vnbeleeuers by warrant of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould haue acceſſe thereto,<note place="margin">He vſeth this word ſo often as being the practiſe where he liued.</note> that ſo they may the ſooner be reclamed by repentance; yet their caſe is otherwiſe who by the Presbytery are <hi>giuen vp to Sathan.</hi> And although that in former time, they were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21485:12"/>not wholly excluded, yet neither were they licenced but reſpectiuely, as hauing need of rather correction than inſtruction, conſcience than ſcience.</p>
            <p>Concerning the end you alleadge very fitly Pope Nicolas ſaying; <hi>That Excommunication, is not poiſon to deſtroy, but Phyſick to recure.</hi> Which is true indeed and cleane cuts the throat of your killing office: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perdy with you to <hi>kill</hi> and to <hi>heale</hi> are two words of one ſignification. For without all queſtion <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> and <hi>brotherly correction</hi> haue both but one end; which end is this, that <hi>A brother may be gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if it be poſsible, the Church edified, the glory of God therby adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced.</hi> So ſaith the apoſtle in expreſſe words: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Firſt it is his purpoſe, <hi>to deliuer vp to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than the inceſtuous perſon for the mortifying of his fleſh, that his ſpirit may be ſaued.</hi> And ſecondly, the wicked man is reiected from Communion with the faithfull; Ieſt the <hi>Church might happily partake in his infection.</hi> His words be theſe:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Caſt you out therfore the old leauen that you may be a new lumpe. Know you not that a little leauen leaueneth the whole maſſe?</hi> Hereout the third <hi>Gods glory,</hi> will eaſily be aduanced, for when mis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Infidels ſhall behold that wicked and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offendours be in no caſe tolerated in the Church, it cannot be but they wil greatly commend the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof <hi>Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Theſe things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, ſo pregnant that they ſtand without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; let vs ſee their agreement and coherence with the practiſed excommunication in the Papacy, which will appeare void and a meere nullity, <hi>Brutum fulmen</hi> rather than a <hi>cenſure of the Church,</hi> or <hi>an holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21485:12"/>
Firſt, it is a right reſting in the whole Church. But the Pope claimes it abſolutely for his owne peculiar, ſo farre as he may abſolue and excommunicate at his pleaſure, yea actually doth <hi>both bind and looſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Franciſ. Vargas in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſp de iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. Epiſcop.</note> in the moſt remote places from him. <hi>The power</hi> (ſaith Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Vargas) <hi>reſteth only in his hands, to Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, Abſolue, Diſpence, Reſerue caſes, Conferre In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, Benefices and ſuch like, to make Lawes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Statutes, puniſh, reward, rule and moderate the Hier archie of the Church. All which power, and if there be any other of like nature hereto, is thought to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon Inferior Biſhops from the chiefe Biſhop alone. And not only ſo, but to reſt in him as in the Originall and ſure head; from whom al other do receiue that wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer which they haue.</hi> As though <hi>Chriſt the ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Well of life,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Fountains from whence</hi> we are willed by Eſay <hi>to draw foorth ſaluation with reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 12.</note> were dried vp, and no hope to attaine eternall life, but by recourſing to the Ceſterns of Rome. Thus neuer did the auncient Councels decree, it was not their intent that all power in the Church ſhould be confined vpon this proud Tarquine. Read and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue but theſe Canons: The 6. of the Nicene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: <hi>Let ancient Cuſtomes bee retained.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Tom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Lybia, Egypt and Pentapolis, let them obey the Biſhop of Alexandria, ſeeing this is the vſage in the Church of Rome. In like maner throughout all other prouinces, let the Metropolitanes of Antioch and Ieruſalem retaine their rights and priuiledges without impeachment.</hi> What ſingular priuiledge or prerogatiue hath the Biſhop of Rome beſtowed on him heere, beyond the other his equall Patriarchs?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21485:13"/>The 13. Canon of the Councell of Antioch.<note place="margin">Concil. Tom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let no Biſhop dare to paſſe from Prouince to Prouince, and giue orders in Churches there, vnleſſe hee bee ſent for by the Metrapolitane and the Biſhops that bee with him. But if not beeing ſent for, or called at all, he ſhall inordinately and inſolently preſume to goe and giue Orders, make Eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions, whereto hee hath no right, let there bee a Nullitie of all his acts, himſelfe be put vnder cenſure for his inſolency, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for his vnreaſonable attempts as condemned by this ſynode for ſuch his preſumption.</hi> What more can we ſay vnto the Biſh. of Rome, who violently intrudes himſelfe without being ſent for into all cauſes in all Churches, taking euery occaſion to intermeddle ſo inſolently and impudently as he doth? Of the ſame argument be the 15.21. and 22. Canons, which expreſly forbid all Biſhops to enter vpon or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with ought in any Dioceſſe beſide their owne. What neede wee more?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 6.</note> In the Aphrican Councel there is a <hi>Prohibition</hi> that the <hi>Biſhop of the firſt Sea</hi> be not called <hi>Prince of Prieſts or chiefe Prieſt,</hi> or by any ſuch like title as theſe, <hi>but only Biſhop of the firſt Sea.</hi> And the 92. Canon of that <hi>Councell</hi> prouides that <hi>no appeales do ſtand good which are made vnto places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea,</hi> (that is to the ſeat of Rome) <hi>and if any man ſhall appeale, he is to be excluded from communion with any within the boundes of Africa.</hi> And hereof there were letters written vnto Caeleſtinus the then Biſhop of Rome, wherein the Africans intreat him, that <hi>he would forbeare from thence forward to receiue into Communion with him, any man excommunicated by them: which ſhould bee derogatorie to the authoritie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21485:13"/>of the Churches of Africa, and the Canons of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Councell. For,</hi> ſay theſe Fathers, <hi>very wiſely and equally haue they prouided, that matters be determined there, and not elſe, but there where firſt they had begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. That it was not to be doubted, but that the ſpirit of grace would be in ſuch ſort preſent in euery prouince, as to inable the Prieſt of Chriſt wiſely to ſee the trueth, and conſtantly to follow it being ſeene, eſpecially ſeeing it was denied none, if he were aggrieued with the ſentence of his Ordinarie to appeale from him to a prouinciall or to a generall Councell, vnleſſe perhaps a man can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God can giue ſeuerall men diſcerning iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deny it, or not giue it vnto many conuening together in a Councell. And ſo</hi> the firſt Nullitie in Excommunication Papall is, the <hi>Incompetencie</hi> (as they terme it) <hi>of the Iudge,</hi> therfore <hi>Incompetent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee vſurpeth on an others right, which the Scholemen themſelues agniſe as ſufficient, to annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſentence of Excommunication: vpon the 4. booke of Sentences, and 18. Diſtinct.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Nullity is, that <hi>Excommunication</hi> is by the <hi>Popes</hi> denounced againſt <hi>Innocents,</hi> as well as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents.</hi> For they vſe to puniſh not them alone againſt whom their quarrells lie, but for ſome one, or few mens ſake they rage againſt <hi>Cities, Prouinces,</hi> whole <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> as is to be ſeene in their <hi>Bulls,</hi> where Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating Kings, Princes, or Magiſtrates; they inſnare together all their Subiects; which wickednes the Lord doth condemne by his prophet:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>The ſonne ſhall not beare the fathers ſinne, but the ſoule which hath ſinned, that ſoule ſhall die.</hi> But this deſtroyer curſeth downe to Hell and deuoureth to perdition, not only
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21485:14"/>the ſon for the fathers fault, but onely whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, * which Auguſtine condemned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 75.</note> but populous cities, whole kingdomes, for the offence, if yet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, of their gouernours. Wherin there is ſome ods betweene Chriſt and him, whoſe Vicar neuertheleſſe he needs wil be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk</hi> 19 10.</note> For * Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he came to ſeeke, and to ſaue that which was loſt:</hi> but the Pope little priſeth myriads of ſoules bought and redeemed with Chriſts bloud, ſo be, he may raigne, and Lord it alone. Chriſt proclaimeth himſelfe <hi>The annointed of Iehoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſuch as mourn in Sion, to giue vnto them beauty for aſhes; the oile of ioy, for mourning; the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, that they might build the old waſte places, and raiſe vp the former deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and repaire the cities that were abandoned and waſte through many generations.</hi> But the Pope turneth vpſide downe Common-wealths ſetled well and in peace, changing mattockes into ſpeares, ſithes into ſwords, and ſheathing ſwords in the bowels of men,<note place="margin">Leo the 10. in whoſe time liued his like, and was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer vnto that houſe, I meane Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Poli who vſed to ſay merily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his fellows, Let vs goe <hi>ad audiendam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulam de Ieſu Chriſto.</hi> In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Let go to Church.</note> forcing kings to quit their kingdomes; altering ſtates, lawes, times at his pleaſure; treading vnder foot the crownes of Emperors, by pretext of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, forcing them to leaue their ſeat royall, and lay their neckes vnder his feet to tread vpon.</p>
            <p>The third nullity is from the cauſes of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. For tell me, whom euer for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or for <hi>Atheiſme</hi> did hee <hi>excommunicate?</hi> Theſe <hi>impieties</hi> paſſe without controlement euen at Rome in the Popes Court, which euery man knows that hath read their ſtories. For to ſay nothing of Idolatry, which by preſcription in the Romane vſe, is now receiued for Religion; was not that Pope a flat Atheiſt who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21485:14"/>in a paſſage of ſpeech with Cardinall <hi>Bembo,</hi> called the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt <hi>a fable?</hi> And what, I pray you, cauſe was there at all why <hi>Henry</hi> the 111. the moſt Chriſtian King of France, ſhould ſo be cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vnleſſe for his too great zeale &amp; forwardneſſe, in the ſuperſtitions of Rome? For as one ſaid very truly:</p>
            <q>
               <l>At Rome you may be what you will,</l>
               <l>So that you be a rakehell ſtill.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But leſt happily I ſeeme ouer ſeuere, againſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions in the firſt Table; hearken what ſome ages ſince, an ey-witneſſe did write:</p>
            <q>
               <l>I tooke a iourney to ſee Rome, and ſince I did it ſee</l>
               <l>I haue inough, Then farewell Rome, I'le come againe to thee</l>
               <l>When Pandar, Brothel, Buffon, or a Cynede I ſhall be.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And leſt I be ſaid to produce nameleſſe authours; do but marke, what <hi>Baptiſta Mantuan,</hi> a Carmelite Frier, hath written of the maners and cuſtomes of Rome.</p>
            <q>
               <l>S. Peters luſt worn family, in riot waſt their daies,</l>
               <l>Exiling far all honeſty, when buffons rents do raiſe</l>
               <l>Vpon Gods owne inheritance, when hallowed altars feed</l>
               <l>Leud loſels, and looſe Catamites, within his Church do breed.</l>
               <l>What maruell though they riſe in wealth, and houſes build on high,</l>
               <l>If Tyrus ſends them ſcarlet gownes, Th'arabian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</l>
               <l>And frankincenſe? they vent out much, temples are ſet to ſale,</l>
               <l>Prieſts, altars, praiers, crownes are ſold, yea heauen, nay God and all.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21485:15"/>
But what do I inſiſt in this, when as <hi>Iohannes Caſa</hi> Archbiſhop of Beneuento and legat Apoſtolique with the Venetians in the daies of Iuly the 111. wrot and publiſhed a booke in Print in Italian rhythmes,<note place="margin">Taxa Cancella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae Apoſtolicae Luter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e apud Toſſ. Dionyſian. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>520.</hi>
               </note> therein extolling the ſinne of Sodomy. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>The taxing of the chancery of Rome,</hi> may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without all contradiction, in what low account be at Rome the moſt grieuous and capitall offences. The words of that booke are theſe: <hi>The Abſolution for him who hath carnally knowen a woman in the church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Groſſus, is the 8. part of an ounce, a ſmall fine for ſuch a fault.</note> 
               <hi>groſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>The Abſolution for him that hath had carnally to doe with his owne mother, ſiſter, goſsip or kinſwoman, groſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Abſolution for him that hath killed his father, mother, ſiſter, brother, or other of his kin, if he be a lay man (for were any of them a Clergy man the murtherer muſt be tied to viſit in perſon the Apoſtolick ſea, groſſ.)</hi> 6. <hi>or</hi> 7. <hi>at moſt. Abſolution for a woman which hath taken downe any potion whereby to deſtroy the Infant conceiued within her, groſſ.</hi> 5. Not to runne vpon particulars, no ſinne ſo enormous, but with mony may be wiped out, without mony no remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For as the old rhythme hath it:</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Court of Rome but for the fleece</l>
               <l>Seekes not the ſheepe at all:</l>
               <l>Opening the doore to all that giue,</l>
               <l>But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> emptie ſtand and call.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Or if you had rather heare the <hi>Taxing of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Chancery,</hi> thus ſaith that booke: <hi>Note you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently that ſuch graces and indulgences be neuer gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto poore men, who becauſe they are not, cannot be comforted. Theſe are not thoſe times, you ſhall know, wherein it was eaſier for a Camell to paſſe thorow the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21485:15"/>eie of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen: But theſe are golden daies indeed, in which Heauen is purchaſed by gold, and ſhut againſt the poore man, becauſe he hath no gold to buy it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the purpoſe. Papall Excommunication, is commonly grounded vpon theſe or ſuch like cauſes: <hi>Priuate Hatred, The Popes Credulitie,</hi> or elſe <hi>Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Paſchall the Second Pope of that name, when Henrie the Fift Emperour Elect came (as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was) to Rome to receiue the Imperiall Crowne of the Popes hand, raiſed ſuch hurlies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince, as put him to ſtand vpon the guard of his life, and brought him to the hazard of his State. When matters were taken vp and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and the Emperour and Pope agreed together, the Pope gaue his word not to aſſay to doe ought which any way might preiudice the Imperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; ſecondly to returne backe againe the right which they had in beſtowing of Biſhopricks. For farther confirmation of which proteſtation, when hee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Sacrament with the Emperor, hee is ſaid to haue vſed this execration. <hi>Let him ſo be diuided from the Kingdome of Chriſt, that ſhall go about to break this agreement, as this part of that life-giuing body is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> And yet for all this, ſcarſe had the Emperor gone out at the City gates, when as the faithleſſe and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Pope, reuerſed whatſoeuer hee did before, caſt <hi>Excommunication</hi> out againſt the Emperour, and ſet new worke in hand againſt him.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bas Vrſperg. in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lippo.</note> 
               <hi>Innocent</hi> the 111. dealt as ſluttiſhly with the <hi>Emperor Philip,</hi> denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him <hi>Excommunicate</hi> for no cauſe elſe, but for pretence of his Predeceſſors cruelty. And when the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21485:16"/>newes was brought him of the mans election to the Empire, hee brake out into theſe franticke and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome ſpeeches: <hi>Either ſhall the Pope take Crowne and Kingdome from Philip, or Philip from the Pope his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall honor.</hi> It is impoſſible to ſumme vp into a breuiarie the froward and tyrannicall Popiſh deſigns and practiſe againſt Emperours and Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates; only two examples ſhall be all I will touch, which both euince his great abuſe of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> and touch the <hi>Venetians</hi> more neere than any elſe, diſcouering the long ſince practiſed tyranny of the Popes againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">At Auinion, where it was for 70. yeeres and more.</note>Pope Clement the fift, who kept his Court * in France, vnderſtanding the <hi>Venetians</hi> had taken in Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara, preſently vpon the newes became ſtark mad, and without delay thundred out his Excommunication againſt them; giuing leaue vnto any man by faire meanes or ſoule to kill as many as hee could,<note place="margin">Pabel. Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Decad. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> beeing now iudged enemies of the Romane church, and caſt forth from the communion of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Supplementum Chronichorum.</note> giuing li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie vnto all Chriſtians whoſoeuer, to arreſt the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> whereſoeuer they met them, to confiſcate their goods, ſell their bodies as ſlaues in the markets: which turned ſo farre vnto their loſſe and detriment, that the State could not trade nor negotiate with any ſtrangers at all, till at length <hi>Francis Dandalo</hi> being ſent vnto France, from the Senate vnto the Pope, and with much adoe admitted vnto his preſence, putting an iron chaine vpon his necke, lay vnder his table, as a ſuppliant ſo long till he got this vngentle Clement to yeeld to let fall his moodineſſe and reſtore the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> to their former ſtate. For which hee was after
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21485:16"/>that called the <hi>Dogge,</hi> becauſe as a dogge he lay chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder the Popes dining table. The ſecond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is of Pope Sixtus the Fourth, who proclaimed warres againſt the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> for helping <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> of <hi>Eſte, Duke of Ferrara</hi> againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> whom the Pope did abet in that quarrell with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporall forces.<note place="margin">Platina in vita Sixti. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> But after their agreement with King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> the ſame man with the power of Appulia ſet vpon the ſame <hi>Venetians,</hi> whom he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had fauoured: and not content, ſtirred vp againſt them the Princes of Italie, as many as hee could,<note place="margin">Supplementum Chronicorum.</note> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced them with his Spirituall curſe, depriued them of all their, whatſoeuer Dominions, to the vtmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his power: Neither in his life time could they obtaine to be releaſed, hauing not any cauſe or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text for his doings more than that hee feared their growing too great, would put himſelfe and other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian Princes to haue cauſe to looke neere vnto themſelues. This was in his time a moſt holy Father,<note place="margin">Petro à Ruuiere Ioan Textor. Weſſel. Gron de Indulgent.</note> whoſe baſe borne ſonne, a worthie Impe of ſuch a Sire, <hi>Peter Cardinall Prieſt of Rome, Patriarch of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> Legat <hi>a Latere</hi> for the Pope, prodigally <hi>ſtantinople,</hi> Legat <hi>a Latere</hi> for the Pope, prodigally lauiſhed in two yeeres ſpace 300000. duckats in lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurie and vaine expenſes, who alſo together with the Cardinall <hi>Saint Lucy,</hi> interceded with his Father for themſelues, and their families, to haue male ſtewes permitted them the three hotteſt moneths of the yeere, and had a grant from that moſt holy Father Sixtus, with this clauſe: <hi>Be it vnto you as you deſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will be replied: It is a new world now, and other manners are now in vſe. And this new world begun and hallowed with their Iubilies, not at Rome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21485:17"/>alone, but euerie Hamlet and Village vnder Romane obeiſance hath brought vs new cauſes of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. But pardon mee. The grounds vpon which the <hi>Venetians</hi> bee excommunicate, are not any whit better than thoſe wee haue rehearſed. For neither is (I trow) the State of the Romiſh religion in hazard there, whereto the <hi>Venetians</hi> are moſt zealouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, nor yet that obedience due, as they call it, to the Apoſtolique Sea: from which they profeſſe and proteſt vnto the world they detract not any thing, which is theirs by diuine right. Neither is it any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of manners, after which though neuer ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly depraued, the Pope makes no inquiſition at al. But it is a queſtion meerely politicall, with which the Popes ſhould not intermeddle, if they do luſt to giue eare vnto Chriſt his Commandement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20.26.</note> or were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to follow his example, who though inuited, would not haue any thing to do with ciuill caſes and legall controuerſies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>A fourth Nullitie is, in that Papall Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, doth not only forbid the parties cenſured, all Eccleſiaſticall Communion, but ouer and aboue, all Politicke and Ciuill:<note place="margin">See the Bulls of Paul the iii ag. Henry the viii. of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. of Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 5. againſt King of Nauar, and Prince of Conde. and of Pius 5. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Queene Elizabeth.</note> as namely that in Mariage, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt the Apoſtles decrees, 1. Cor. 7.8. and lawfull ſubiection vnto Magiſtrates. For it is their manner in their Bulls Excommunicatorie, to abſolue the ſubiects from their Othe of Obedience, and any other bond or dutie in which they bee tied: to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the poſſeſſions and goods of Princes as a pray and a ſpoile to any that will ſeeke them, ſo as it ſhall be lawfull without denouncing warre, proclaiming hoſtilitie, by ſecret practiſes, or open force for any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21485:17"/>man to purſue, to apprehend or murther them, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue their iſſue of al right to ſucceed, and make them infamous and vncapable: to Incite the Nobilitie and Comminaltie to armes, Interdict the ſuſpended from any commerce or negotiation with other nations: to determine the leagues and articulations of Princes, and States made with them, to be void and of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditie; and laſtly, to forbid them Chriſtian buriall. Which, what is it elſe but in deteſtable ſort to violate the law of Nature and Nations, to ſet vp iniuſtice euerie where, to teach children to hate their parents, ſubiects to be periured, perfidious, rebellious, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, and practiſe ſuch Papall virtues as theſe? And therefore it was not without cauſe that Lauren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Valla a Putritian of Rome, ſaid: <hi>That Rome was a ſchoole wherein men learned to lie, to deceiue, ſweare, forſweare.</hi> Chriſt taught no ſuch leſſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21.</note> when hee bad; <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the things that bee Caeſars, and vnto God that which belongs vnto him.</hi> It is not the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Saint Paul,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> who willeth <hi>euerie ſoule to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto higher Powers. Whether Apoſtle, or Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, or Prophet, or whoſoeuer hee bee,</hi> ſaith Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome; for this ſubiection doth not in any caſe croſſe our pietie. Peter gaue no ſuch command, when hee willeth ſeruants to bee ſubiect in all feare vnto their Lords, not vnto the good and gentle alone,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2</note> but euen the froward and peruerſe. Happily it will be ſaid, <hi>but not Excommunicated.</hi> Surely yes, if the perſon which ſtands Excommunicate, be not any otherwiſe to bee accounted of, then as an Ethnicke, and a Publicane: with whom in ciuill negotiations the Iewes did not refraine to communicate. For liuing in and vnder
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21485:18"/>an * <hi>Ethnicke ſtate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Romans by deputies.</note> they yeelded obedience vnto thei poſitiue lawes, and to the Publicans (Farmers of the common reuenues) they paied Cuſtomes and tribute mony, trading alſo with them in other things. Which right whenſoeuer the Popes of Rome went about to infringe by thundring curſes and Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, God from Heauen hath diſcloſed the fearfulneſſe of his vengeance againſt the forſworne Traitors: as is plaine in that miſerable end of Ralfe Duke of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,<note place="margin">Antoninus vita Henr. <hi>4.</hi> Abbas V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſperg Hen. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; alij.</note> whom Gregorie the Seauenth did ſet vp in place of the Emperour Henrie the Fourth. Which Ralph, being at the will of the Pope crowned by the Arch-Biſhop of Mentz, wretched man that he was, for in lieu of a vaine crowne which ſtood not long vpon his head, hee vnderwent an infortunate croſſe: beeing vanquiſhed in fight by his Prince, who when hee yeelded vp the ghoſt, ſhewed his right hand cut off in fight, as a memoriall of his treachery vnto the Biſhops his Inſtigators, vſing withall theſe wordes: <hi>See you heere that hand with which I bound my ſelfe by ſolemne oth neuer to iniurie, neuer to contriue againſt my Lord Henrie: which oth to breake, your perſwaſion, and the Apoſtolicall commandement hath induced mee. Behold and conſider, in how right a courſe yee haue led him that was content to be ruled by you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift Nullitie of papall Excommunication re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth behind, to bee drawen from the end of that Cenſure, which is the ſauing of his Soule, in ſetting foorth the glorie of God, procuring the good of the Church. Theſe ends how little root they haue euer taken (time out of minde) in the Popes of Rome, all good men haue well noted, and many, not the worſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21485:18"/>haue deplored. <hi>Roderico</hi> biſhop of Zamora,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roder. Zamor. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>ſpei vitae hum ca<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 3. Caſtellane that is, keeper of the Caſtle Saint Angelo.</note> * Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellane &amp; Referendary to Pope Paul the 2. in his booke intituled, <hi>The glaſſe of mans life,</hi> where he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the anxieties &amp; cares which do accompany al Popes, hath theſe words: <hi>Their firſt let and hinderance are domeſticall cares, then their vniuſt deſire, or to ſpeak plaine, greedie greedineſſe, to aduance their kindred, and which fleſh and blood doth reueale vnto them, to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate their linage, kindred and name.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The houſe of Parma at this day from Paul the third a Farneſcan.</note> 
               <hi>For ſo haue ſome Popes been reſolued to make themſelues the rootes and raiſers not of one but many noble and famous houſes, the firſt progenitors of mightie Princes. Such aſpiring de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, want not the Preſidents of ancient Popes, much leſſe ſhall they want fautors and furtherers. Learned and vnlearned will perſwade them to it, ſome will cite fables, ſome alleadge Scriptures and detorted authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to tickle the Popes itching eares.</hi> (Heare him what he ſaith (good Baronius) and learne of him what counſell to giue your Pope Paul.) <hi>Loe,</hi> will they ſay, <hi>What man euer hated his owne fleſh? For Chriſt himſelf whoſe actions euery Pope his Vicar ſhould follow, when he loued his owne, loued them vnto the end. He exalted thoſe that were allied vnto him. But whether did he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt them vnto the croſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſar Borgia. Guicciard. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Hiſt. Ital.</note> And this mind doubt had Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, when he raiſed his ſonne <hi>Caeſar,</hi> from a Cardinals hat, to the royall dignity of <hi>Duke of Valentia,</hi> by prophane chaffare of holy things. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith <hi>Nicolaus de Clamengijs,</hi> ſpeaking of Popes) <hi>when exceeding great abundance of worldly plenty and inſatiable auarice, aſſociated with ambition, had ſeated themſelues in Clergymen, treading downe the vertuous branches of ancient better daies, as it could
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21485:19"/>not but fall out, ſo it came to paſſe, Pride made themſwel, deſire of great place puffed them vp, they waſted their daies and bodies in wantonneſſe. Three Lords they had cruell exactors to content, Luxury firſt, which exacted vpon them, the pleaſures of wine, of ſleepe, of feaſtings, of muſicke, of Iugles, of pandars, of whores. Secondly Pride, which would haue the pompous pageantly ſhewes of high ſtoried houſes, Caſtels, Towers, Pallaces, royall and gorgeous furniture, gay apparrell, horſes retinue. Thirdly, Auarice vnſatiable, which prouided and ſtored vp heaps of coine, to maintaine the premiſed brauerie; or at leaſt if that needed not, to feede their eies, and giue them content in viewing the ſtamp of their come. To fulfill the beheſt of theſe Lordes, and accompliſh all their deſires, the golden age of Saturne (whereof the Poets fable) would vneth ſuffice, if againe the world might behold ſuch times. And becauſe not any though neuer ſo fatte a Biſhopricke, is able ſufficiently to content theſe three Harpyes, they haue bethought them of other helps and furtherances in the caſe. For the Popes perceiuing, how that the profits and reuenues of the Romane Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, the Patrimonie of Saint Peter greater than king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, though none indeed very much impaired, by their negligence would not bee inough to maintaine the credit and height of that State, which they as Emperors and kings of Nations were determined to exalt: therfore they haue intruded vpon other mens flocks which broght forth yong in multitudes, yelded plenty of wool &amp; milk.</hi> Thus you ſee the cauſes which moued the Popes to trie ſo many waies to bring them in treaſure, abuſing their office and paſtorall charge in euery particular point thereof: as if Chriſt had commanded them not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21485:19"/>to feed the flocke, but to fleece them, to flea them, to bowell them, to eat them. For to begin with their incroachments: they haue not onely ſeiſed the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Biſhops, and collations of all Eccleſiaſticall dignities into their owne hands, aboliſhing the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent right of elections; but (to ſpeake in the phraſe of <hi>Nic. de Clamengijs</hi>) <hi>that the golden currents might flow more abundantly from all partes of the world into their Court, they haue debard &amp; depriued all Dioceſans &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of their right of prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation, or any way diſpoſing of their benefices; forbidding vpon pain of their curſe</hi> (ſee what vſe they make of excommunication) <hi>that they be not ſo preſumptuouſly bold</hi> (for in ſuch termes their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts do run) <hi>as to inſtitute any man vnto any benefice vnder their charge, vntill thoſe were prouided for, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, or did refuſe to accept that benefice, vnto whom they had giuen any aduouſins themſelues in reuerſion. Since which time, good God, what ſwarmes haue there been in all places, at all times, of thoſe that haue gaped for ſuch preſentations! Men taken not from the ſtudy or from the ſchooles, but from the plough and manuary trades, to haue charge of ſoules and paſtorall cares com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them. Men that vnderſtood the Arabian tongue aſwell as they did the Latin</hi> (a perfect patern of our times) <hi>that could hardly read, nay more, I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſpeake it, not able to know</hi> A <hi>from</hi> B.</p>
            <p>And theſe exactions not yet ſufficing to ſatiate the rauen of the Romiſh Popes and Cardinals,<note place="margin">The words at creation of a Cardinall be: <hi>Eſto Princeps mundi &amp; frater noſter.</hi>
               </note> ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſhifts were yet further inuented to get and heape money vnto their cofers, whereof this is no place to ſpeake. For the Colledge of Cardinals growing daily greater, the burthen grew greater vpon all countries,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21485:20"/>Becauſe it it was held an abſurd thing, that ſuch as were aduanced to that place in the Church, as to bee fellowes vnto kings, ſhould not bee prouided in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable ſort, but ſtand as hungry and ſtarueling mercenaries. So that to maintaine and beare out this pride, all States both Temporall and Eccleſiaſticall were oppreſſed. From hence came the retaining of ſo many benefices and preferments, in nature repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant one to another, while the ſame man is, both a Moncke and a Canon, <hi>Regular</hi> and <hi>Secular,</hi> vnder one ſeuerall hab it, hauing &amp; enioying the <hi>Rights, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, Offices, Benefices,</hi> of all Religions, Orders, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions. Inſomuch as that ſpeech ſpoken of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, <hi>A Ieſuit is a man of all profeſsions,</hi> may better be fitted vnto the Cardinals. <hi>Peter of Aliaco Cardinall of Cambray</hi> in his booke of <hi>Reforming the ſtate of the Church</hi> which he wrot and preſented to the Councell of Conſtance, is very earneſt to haue theſe abuſes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, where he calleth thoſe Pluralities of Church-liuings, a <hi>monſtrous, and many waies ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous offence.</hi> This is the cauſe why Iubilies and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences be ſo dearely bought,<note place="margin">See the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred grieuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many. grieu 3.</note> that they draw foorth the gold &amp; godly life of whole kingdoms, as the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; States of Germany complained at the Diet at Norimberge in the yeare 1522. Their gold is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loined, being by the impious Collectors of Rome tranſported out of the country into Rome, godlineſſe is baniſhed and cleane extinct, while men preſuming vpon abſolution, let looſe the reines of liberty vnto all impiety.</p>
            <p>To conclude, this bottomleſſe pit of greedy deſire hath ſent foorth excommunications and curſings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21485:20"/>Princes and Magiſtrates, as may plainly bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted by theſe examples. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth charged <hi>Frederic</hi> the Emperour, that vpon paine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cenſure, he ſhould with all expedition and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpeed,<note place="margin">Platina in the life of Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the ninth.</note> paſſe into Aſia againſt the Infidels. And becauſe he was thought to make no very great haſte, as he had threatned, he accurſed him indeed. <hi>Frederic</hi> appalled at this proceeding, beſought the Pope that he might be aſſoiled, but could in no caſe obtaine it, till he had paid in, to the vie of the Church of Rome 120000. ounces of gold. King Iohn of England, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding excommunicate by Pope Innocent the 3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paulus Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius.</hi> Platina in the life of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the 3.</note> fearing the French King would get his kingdome from him, whom the Pope had incited to warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; that he might bee receiued into grace with his fatherhood, was conſtrained to make Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland his tributarie States, and for them to pay yearely vnto Rome 100. markes of gold: which <hi>Peter</hi> (whoſe ſucceſſour he vaunteth to bee) I thinke would neuer haue done, who ſo conſtantly refuſed <hi>Simon Magus</hi> money: <hi>Thy money bee together with thee to perdition, that ſuppoſeſt Gods gifts can be bought with money.</hi> Their chaffaring of holy things ſo as they doe, is proofe they ſucceed <hi>Simon,</hi> not <hi>Peter,</hi> but <hi>Magus.</hi> And to draw all vnto an iſſue,<note place="margin">By a ſtatute of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as it were.</note> what other cauſe in truth is there now of this their contending with, and excommunicating the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> but this, that the carefull wiſe Magiſtrate would reſtraine in ſome ſmall meaſure that Romiſh rauin and inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rapine?</p>
            <p>And ſo your Popes cenſure, <hi>ô Baronius,</hi> being clearely proued ſo many waies void, ought not in any
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21485:21"/>ſort to be feared, eſpecially now in theſe daies of ours, in which the light of the Goſpell hath certainely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed what is the true vſe of Excommunication, which for ſo many ages paſt, the Popes haue, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſtrange illuſions, changed into a moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious tyranny.<note place="margin">Plinius lib. <hi>8.</hi> ca. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> They write, that the Lion a fierce and cruell beaſt, is exceedingly afraid of the running of cart wheeles, and empty coatches, but eſpecially trembles at the ſight of fire. Theſe Lions of Venice are not ſo, who often heeretofore being deluded with the vaine rumbling of the Papall curſings, haue ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med now at laſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galli,</hi> alluding to the French in the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of words who heertofore ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Popes againſt Venice. The Armes of France. Saint Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies fire. <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. Muſhromes much eaten in Italy, and haue a poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous qualitie in them ſaith Atheneus. But he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the pride and vanitie, the word being <hi>fungus. In faſciculo rerum expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendarum.</hi>
               </note> that your fire is no better than a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted flame, and the thunder-cracks of your terrible <hi>Salmoneus,</hi> no more to be feared then childrens rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. For ſo long as the Cocks ſet not vp their combes, not affright with their crowing, the howling of theſe night birds are but toies. Or what cauſe is there why the Lions of Venice ſhould be afraid of your fire who carrie about them <hi>Lilies,</hi> an excellent remedie, as Phyſitians write, againſt the diſeaſe called <hi>Ignis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer;</hi> and not ſo alone, but as Pliny writeth, againſt the ſtinging of ſerpents and poiſon of muſhromes?</p>
            <p>Indeed I confeſſe the lightning of Gods ſeruants is not raſhly to bee vilepended, and yet there is no cauſe to ſtand in feare therof alwaies, eſpecially when, as Vdalrichus Huttenus a knight of Germany writeth it proceedeth from <hi>Humane paſſion.</hi> I tremble at the indignation of Chriſt; I feare not the diſpleaſure of the Pope; and this is not Chriſts cauſe, but the Popes quarrell. Theſe nets are not caſt to catch ſoules, but to draw in gold and ſiluer: for ſeeing that the late <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of Clement the Eight againſt the ſtate of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21485:21"/>thriued ſo well, as to enlarge Peters patrimonie with an acceſſe, of not a ſew townes theſe <hi>Scarlet Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> haue made them ſelues a promiſe, that this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Venice</hi> ſhall ſpeed as well. But I wiſh them take heed, leſt <hi>Ill counſell fall heauieſt on the giuers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohan de Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuilla lib. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venetians</hi> by their long continued trade with the Grecians, may happely haue learned to anſwere Paul 5. to the ſame purpoſe as the Greekes ſometimes did Iohn the two and twentieth: <hi>Wee beleeue thy au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is within thy owne dominions ſupreme: we can not indure thy pride, which is extreamen: we are not able to ſatiate thy Auarice. The Diuell be with thee, becauſe God is with vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore to returne from whence we haue digreſſed: by the premiſes (Baronius) you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, the vanitie and follie of that your exhortation which you annex vnto your Pope.<note place="margin">B</note> 
               <hi>Go on then a Gods name holy Father, as you haue begun, &amp; ſuppoſe not that no man can iuſtly tax your too much haſtineſſe,</hi> &amp;c. For it had been your part firſt to haue proued the thing right and honeſt, wherto you would lead him, which failing to do, you ſhall haue no thankes for your idle attempt in ſeeking to match Paul your Pope in equall termes with Paul the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, much leſſe to preferre him before, and incite him as you do, to proceed. There is no delay can excuſe, much leſſe commend that which originally was vniuſt: nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the longer debated &amp; demurred, the greater the fault in execution. But this palpable flatterie makes me remember a worthie ſaying of <hi>Roderigo</hi> Biſhop of Zamora:<note place="margin">In ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritae hum. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Pope though he hath all things a yet euermore ſtands in need of one thing,</hi> viz.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21485:22"/>
               <hi>a faithfull Counſellor to tell him the trueth: For from the higheſt vnto the loweſt, euerie one is giuen to ſooth him vp, they tell him ſmooth tales, but all to deceiue him: Cunningly they aduiſe him, for their owne aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: Fraudulently they ſupplicate to attaine their own wiſhes; and for that flatterie is aſſociate with guile, as euery man can tell, they combine among themſelues like craftie companions as they bee, not to croſſe or thwart the one the other. And as the ſcope of an Orator is to perſwade, the end of Phyſicke is to recure; ſo the intent of a flatterer is to colour and deceiue. The fowlers call is a pleaſing note, but the end is to deceiue the bird: And as Ierome ſaid once; Poiſons are giuen mixt with hony. Theſe are the men that make God and the Pope fellowes, aſcribing ſome Deitie vnto him. But and if I miſtake not the trueth, the Popes ſhould indeed heerein ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like God, if they would command ſuch Varlets to the halter; but out of all doubt, true ſeruers of God, if ſuch cooſining deceiuers were well puniſhed for their paines.</hi> So far that Biſhop. But that which I maruell at moſt of all, is, that <hi>Baronius,</hi> a man who knoweth all things, the skilfulleſt antiquarie in the Church ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that liueth, the man, <hi>who when firſt hee gaue his mind to write,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſed out of Terence.</note> 
               <hi>ſet it downe as his principall intent and purpoſe, that the lies he committed to the preſſe, might finde acceptance with the vulgar ſort,</hi> that hee ſhould ſet down ſo barſh a comparison of Paul the fift, with <hi>Gregorie the Seuenth, and Alexander the third;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt was the vileſt Varlet that euer ſate in that ſea, and the latter to bee deteſted for his intolerable pride.<note place="margin">B</note> 
               <hi>I for my part,</hi> (ſo you ſay) <hi>do profeſſe ingenuouſly that I reioice in my Spirit, I will ſay with the Apoſtle,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21485:22"/>I do ouerabound in ioy.</hi> And let mee alſo ſpeake in the Apoſtles wordes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>God ſhall ſmite thee thou painted wall,</hi> that dareſt belch foorth of thy vnſanctified throat the wordes of ſo great an Apoſtle, who as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly canſt ſay with a pure conſcience which hee once ſpake, <hi>I vſe great boldneſſe of ſpeech toward you,<hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I glorie greatly in you, I am filled with comfort, and am exceedingly ioyous in all our tribulation,</hi> as thou canſt thoſe former words of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>I haue wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged no man, I haue corrupted no man, I haue defrauded no man:</hi> when the words thou ſpeakeſt, theſe verie wordes, are only to <hi>wrong, to defraud, to corrupt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">B</note> But let vs heare the iuſt cauſe of this ſo ſupera bounding ioy. * <hi>When I behold in my decrepit age Gregorie or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander in Peters chaire.</hi> Heare ô you Kings, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ô Princes, giue eare ô Potentates of the Chriſtian world; by the teſtimonie of <hi>Caeſar Baronius,</hi> a Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend old man, a ſincere Cardinall, an eie witneſſe, a man of credit, <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſitteth in Peters chaire, not (you muſt know) Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, whoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſpeech this is; <hi>I ſpeake it with confidence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. in epiſt. lib. <hi>4</hi> epiſt. <hi>30.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be, that names himſelfe, or would be named, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Biſhop, in that his pride, hee ſheweth himſelfe the forerunner of Antichriſt, that aduaunceth himſelfe beyond all equalls:</hi> who calleth the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Biſhop,</hi> wherein the now Popes do ſo much glory, a Swelling, a new name, a word of raſhneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the 2. and 24. epiſties of the 4. and 6. booke.</note> Proud, Pompaticall, Peruerſe, Superſtitious, Prophane, Impious, a Name of Error, of Singularity, Vanitte, Hypocriſie, Blaſphemie.</hi> That Gregorie, I ſay, the firſt of his name, who wrote with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of Arian Princes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Whereof I would haue
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21485:23"/>you informe your gratious ſoueraignes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ep.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>That ſeruant, would haue made my ſelf a party in contriuing the deſtruction of the Lumbards, there had not been any nation at this day of that name to haue had either King, or Duke, or Earie. But becauſe I feare God, I dare not make a party to deſtroy any man.</hi> This is not the man who ſits in Peters chaire, but, at which my hart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that Gregory, who firſt was called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> as much as,<note place="margin">see Antonin. p. 2. Benno the Cardinal, of the life, and acts of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the VII. otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand the life of Henry iiii. Sigebert, and others.</note> 
               <hi>A fire brand of hell,</hi> Gregory, I ſay, that Coniurer, the Monke, who curſed the Emperour Henry iiii. and made him come vnto him ſo farre as <hi>Canuſium,</hi> without his robes royall, in woollen cloth, bare footed and bare legged, in a ſharpe win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and there for all the meanes he could make by himſelfe, by mediators, in moſt baſe ſort ſubmitting himſelfe, yet made him dance attendance three whole daies. Who hauing at laſt receiued him to grace, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another forged quarrell, did accurſe him again, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued him of his ancient hereditary right in collation of Eccleſiaſticall preferments, and made that moſt vnequall and intolerable conſtitution, which princes ſhould in no caſe ſuffer: <hi>If heereafter any man do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the inueſture into a Biſhopricke or an Abbey, at the hand of any lay perſons, let him in no caſe be held as an Abbat or Biſhop, nor haue audience, as an Abbat or Biſhop: and moreouer wee denie him the grace of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forbid him to come within the Church.</hi> That Gregory who abſolued the Princes of Germanie from the oath of allegeance which they haue taken, cauſing them to take the field againſt their ſoueraigne and lawfull Prince by him depoſed: ſetting vp Ralph
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21485:23"/>Duke of Sweueland in his roome, vnto whom hee ſent a crowne of gold with this motto:</p>
            <q>
               <l>The rocke to Peter gaue the crowne</l>
               <l>Peter to Radolph ſends it downe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That Gregory ſate in Peters chaire, who at length was abandoned of his owne men, ſaw the city of Rome ſurpriſed, himſelfe laid priſoner in Creſcentius or Angels Caſtell, after that exiled to Selerno, where he confeſſed his capitall treaſon againſt Saint Peter, Gods Church, his Lord the Emperour, which by the Diuels perſwaſion hee put in practiſe, and ſo in horrible anguiſh and torment of mind miſerably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his wretched daies; hauing formerly in the Councels of Brixia and Mentz, beene depriued of all Papall dignitie, condemned as a breaker of good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Church, as a diſturber of the Empire, a ſower of ſcandals, a church-robber, a magitian, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe from the ſaith, giuen to diuinations and to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, one that had a familiar ſpirit with him.</p>
            <p>And as for Alexander the third, his pride intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appeareth hence. <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond of that name, being by him formerly excommunicate, came vnto Venice to make his peace with him, promiſing to vnder goe any penance; the agreement paſſed betweene them ſo, Alexander the Pope ſtanding in the doore of S. Markes Church, in the view and ſight of all people, bad the Emperour caſt himſelfe downe vpon the ground, and there in open audience deſire abſolution, which he accompliſhing, the Pope ſetting his foot vpon the Emperors necke, ſaid theſe words: It is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt walke vpon the Aſpe and the Baſiliske, thou ſhalt tread the Lion and the Dragon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21485:24"/>foot.</hi> The Emperour heereat proteſting he did it not <hi>To him but to Peter,</hi> the Pope replied, <hi>Both to mee and Peter:</hi> putting himſelfe not only aboue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, but before S. Peter alſo.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the men, <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the III. whom Baronius calleth, the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall rootes of the decaied liberty of the Church.</hi> And with whom he dareth match <hi>Paul</hi> the Fift, preſent Pope. Surely it bodeth no good to Kings, to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the Chriſtian world, vnleſſe he miſſed happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his parallels, which I rather thinke the man did, than that the Chriſtian world ſhould feare any ſuch vaine coniecturall opinion.<note place="margin">And hee had almoſt beene in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claue of Leo the eleuenth, wanting but 5. or 6. voices.</note> But ſo the caſe ſtandeth, <hi>Baronius,</hi> if he will be ſome body, I had almoſt ſaid, if he will be Pope, muſt reſolue vpon ſomewhat wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the halter, or the hangman.</p>
            <p>But happily heere he will except and ſay, <hi>The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Henry</hi> was a moſt froward and peruerſe man, and ſo worthy to be handled as he was by <hi>Hildebrand.</hi> But ſure both are falſe: For neither was he ſuch as you defame him, nor if he had beene, was he ſo to be vſed of Chriſt his Vicar, who ought to haue hearkned vnto his Maſters words;<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>11.</hi> Infaſciculo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum expetenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>Learne of me, for and humble minded.</hi> That the Prince was not ſo, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his life, written by one that lined in thoſe daies, not very long after his death: where hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him high commendations, for his loue to God, liberality to the poore, iuſt carriage toward all. <hi>I haue not,</hi> ſaith the writer, <hi>any priuate cauſe of griefe, piety compels me to bewaile the publick loſſe; when he left vs, iuſtice left the earth, peace went away, treachery ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in place of faithfulneſſe, the Quire of Gods ſeruants
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21485:24"/>held their peace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Monaſteries loſt their patron, Cloyſters their Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Alas, what a loſſe hadſt thou ô Mentz, in ſo worthy a workemaſter, to repaire the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of thy Monastery! Had he liued to conſummate the worke begun in thee, he had made it anſwer able to that famous pile at Spire, where hee raiſed the Monasterie from the ground, and brought it to perfection, ſo huge a piece of building, ſo beautified exceedingly with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ingrauerie, equall, nay exceeding the praiſe and commendation of all the antick monuments of kings</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As for you poore people, you haue cauſe to grieue, for now you are become poore indeed, hauing loſt your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter in your pouerty: he fed you with his owne hands, he waſhed you, he clothed all your nakedneſſe; Lazarus lay not before his gate, but was ſet downe at his table.</hi> But with you, <hi>Baronius,</hi> as to <hi>Kill</hi> and <hi>Feed</hi> is all one, ſo is there no difference betweene piety and peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: or to ſpeake in plaine termes, Thoſe are the <hi>Peruerſeſt men</hi> aliue with you, who take a way know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your peruerſeneſſe. But it is no maruell this good Emperor is ſo ſtiled by you, who durſt ſharpen your railing pen againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the iiii. the preſently moſt <hi>Chriſtian French King,</hi> by the hand of God preſerued hitherto, to ſuruiue all murthering emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſubornd againſt him, and worthy to line <hi>Neſtors</hi> yeares. For if you remember, in the Epiſtle to <hi>Pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garolla</hi> prefixed before the firſt Tome of your <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales,</hi> ſpeaking there of the ſiege of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tem. An. ex editione Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt. <hi>1601.</hi>
               </note> a a towne that ſtood againſt the King, thus you write: <hi>But yet at length, though ſomewhat late, wicked Bena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad,</hi> ſo you terme his moſt Chriſtian Maieſty, <hi>in vain aſſaulting that City, wherein Eliſeus</hi> you meane <hi>Pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garola,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21485:25"/>the firebrand of war and Doctor of treaſon, <hi>ſeeing all his hopes daſhed and come to naught, hath left the ſiege and is diſlodged:</hi> which words, leſt they might incenſe the King, are, I know not by whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe raſed one of that copy, which is in the Kings libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Paris,</hi> the leafe being taken out of the booke, as by the letters in the Regiſter appeares, but may bee found and ſeene, in all other copies whatſoeuer that go abroad in mens hands. Thus you make no bones to call the Lords anointed moſt <hi>Impious, Wilfull, Bena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dads</hi> Nay you prefer the butchering of them, for ſo haue ſome of your Popes done, before the worke of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> as is euident by the ſpeech of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth, which he made vnto the Cardinals in the Conſiſtorie at Rome the xj of September in the yeere 1589. vpon the murther of Henrie the Third.</p>
            <p>Come wee now to that concluſion which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from the ſuch worthy premiſes before ſpecified. You haue the ſame triall,<note place="margin">B</note> you ſay, <hi>to try.</hi> Againſt whom good Sir? What, againſt the Venetians? See how fitly your proofe doth fit the purpoſe. <hi>Theſe ruines</hi> lie,<note place="margin">B</note> that I may ſay with Eſay, <hi>in your handes.</hi> I acknowledge Eſaies words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.</note> and withall confeſſe that hee foreſheweth the State of the people of the Iewes ſhall be ſo full of trouble, of miſerie, ſo farre paſt hope of al recouery, that it ſhal be impoſſible to find a man, who vpon any intreaty wil take vpon him the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ordering of that State, for feare of dangers and deſpaire of doing good. <hi>One ſhall take a friend of his owne kindred by the boſome and ſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 3 6.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, thou ſhalt bee our head, and ſtay this mine with thy hand.</hi> Then what followes? <hi>But he ſhall ſwear and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21485:25"/>ſay I can not help you. I will not bee your Lord, there is neither meat nor clothing in my houſe, make mee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ruler of the people.</hi> The Venetians, I dare ſay, wil vſe no ſuch ſpeech vnto your Pope, neither if they ſhould, would the Pope make them the Prophets anſwer, vnleſſe peraduenture in ſome ſuch ſort as hee vſeth in the day of his Conſecration, when riſing vp from his dirty ſeat, after the Cardinals vttered theſe ſpeeches; <hi>He raiſeth the lowly out of the duſt, and the poore out of the mire, that he may ſet him with Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ceremon. ſect. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and poſſeſſe the ſeat of glorie,</hi> to take out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlains lappe ſitting by him, as much mony as hee can graſpe in his hand, (and yet there is neither ſiluer or gold in his lappe, nor doth hee take any out) and caſt it vnto the people, with theſe words, <hi>Siluer and gold haue I none:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4</note> Or elſe when he is bereft of all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, vſurped (as one day he muſt needs be, according to that Prophecy Reuel. 17.16.) then he ſhal be inforced to ſay: <hi>In my houſe is neither bread nor clothing.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that you haue any reference, or that it is your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to forſpeak that, I do not, nor I can not ſay it.</p>
            <p>It is not my purpoſe to inſiſt vpon that which followeth in Baronius his writing, leſt I might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloy the reader. For that which hee hath touching <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the promiſe made vnto him, hath been ſo often alledged and refuted, that to ſhape an anſwer thereto, were againe to do which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die done, and to haue my labour for my pains. For as that vngratious Iulian being beſide his right wits, would haue it be beleued,<note place="margin">Socrates in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Eccleſ.</note> that the ſoul of Great <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> was in him; ſo the Popes of Rome, out of the ſame phrenſie, do perſwade themſelues that Saint
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21485:26"/>Peters ſoule by right of Succeſſion dwelleth in them. And therupon whatſoeuer honour or right Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had, they claime it as hereditarie vnto themſelues, and make it their owne: And ſo inſtile themſelues <hi>Peters Succeſſors.</hi> For though we ſhould grant that this promiſe alleadged, <hi>And the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile,</hi> did belong to Peter alone, which yet is falſe and not granted, what hath the pope to do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with? or what hath he to do with Saint Peter? what one thing is there wherein he doth partake with him? In preaching the Goſpell? but the Pope prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not. In feeding the Flocke? neither doth hee feed any flocke. In exalting himſelfe aboue Kings and Princes? Peter did not ſo, hee neuer ſo much as drempt thereof. What then? In ſucceſſion vnto and ſitting in Peters chaire at Rome? But Peter when that priuiledge was conferred on him by Chriſt, was in <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> not at Rome, and ſhould haue enioied it, although he neuer had ſeene Rome. Away then with this Pythagoricall Tranſanimation, by which the ſoule of Peter, the Indowments of Peter, the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Peter, are transfuſed and go vnto all Silueſters, all Hildebrandes, all Sergiuſſes, or Hogges ſnouts, all Iulies, Sixties, Gregories the Succeſſors of Peter.</p>
            <p>That which you alleadge, Baronius, out of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; <hi>I haue made the a Pillar of iron, and a wall of braſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1. B</note> deſerueth to bee laughed at and contemned. As if that good man Ieremie, who ſubiected himſelfe vnto the ſtate of Kings, and by them was caſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, againſt whom the Princes, and people, men and woemen, great and ſmall, did barke and exclaime, were masked in robes royall, and led along with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21485:26"/>princely pompe, his Papall triple diademe on his head, to rule the rulers of the earth, and reigne ouer them with plenary power? or as if a man might ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, not be held a mad man for his ſuch imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that long before the birth of Chriſt the firſt ſtone of the Papacie was laid in Ieremie. Such like franticks bee thoſe fellowes who conceit that the originall of Monckerie was from Elias, or yet more ancient from <hi>Adam,</hi> (a Gods name) before Eue was made out of his ſide.</p>
            <p>This is ridiculous, but that which followeth, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous; and what Chriſtian eare can endure to hear it, that this Paraſite claweth his Pope withall? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you ſtand as a rocke in the church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">B <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>againſt which which who ſo daſheth, ſhall be daſhed in pieces;</hi> which euen by the witneſſe of Saint Peter, is nothing elſe, then to caſt Chriſt Ieſus, to whom alone this doth agree,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet</hi> 2.</note> from his high Throne of Maieſtie. Yet this is that ſmooth eloquence of Rome, not miſliked by the Popes: from whence theſe flowers of the Canoniſts came; <hi>The Pope is in Primacie Abel, in Zeale Elias, in Mildneſſe Dauid, in Power Peter, in Vnction Chriſt.</hi> From whence that acclamation came, directed once vnto the Pope: <hi>Thou art all, and ouer all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the laſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> 
               <hi>All power is giuen thee in Heauen and Earth.</hi> But lie and flatter as faſt as you can, Chriſt at length will winne the day. And that ſeducer Sathan, together with the beaſt and falſe prophet ſhall bee caſt into the lake of fire and brimſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.</note> and be tormented day and night for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen ſo Lord Ieſu come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="papal_bull">
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:27"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21485:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE BVLL OF POPE PAVLVS the Fift, againſt <hi>the Common wealth and</hi> Senate of Venice: With the Proteſtation of the ſaid Duke <hi>and senate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>AVL Biſhops, Seruant of the Seruants of God. To our moſt deare and venerable brethren the Patriarches, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and our beloued Sons, Vicars, Abbats, Priors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prelates aſwell Secular as Regular, and other perſons Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, appointed and ordeined throughout the whole Common wealth and Seigniory of Venice, Salutations and Apoſtolike benediction. We haue beene giuen to vnderſtand that the Duke and Senate of the Common wealth and Seigniory of Venice haue for certaine yeares made in their Councels ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and diuers Decrees and Statutes, contrary, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the authority of the Sea Apoſtolike, liberty and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21485:28"/>immunity of the Church, to generall Councels and Sacred Canons: but alſo to the conſtitutions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Biſhops of Rome. And amongſt others that about the 23. of May in the yeare 1602. taking occaſion of certaine proceſſe and difference moued betweene Doctor F. Zabarella, on the one part, and the Monkes of the Monaſtery of Praxilia of the order of S. Bennet, otherwiſe S. Iuſtin in the Dioceſſe of Padoua on th'other part: They had ordeined that the foreſaid Monkes from thencefoorth, and for alwaies after ſhould haue no action for, vnder any title or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour whatſoeuer, to be preferred vpon the goods Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall poſſeſſed by laie perſons vnder title of Emphiteuſe, and cannot by right of preference or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of the propriety with the vſufruit, or of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction of the perſons compriſed in the inueſtiture, or for any other cauſe challenge vnto themſelues the propriety of the foreſaid goods, but only the right of the direct dominion: declaring that this ſhall take place, <hi>Doreſnauant,</hi> hereafter, aſwel for th'other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Eccleſiaſticall, Monaſteries and other religions places being in their Seigniory and territory of their obedience. And about the ſixteenth of Ianuary 1603. renuing (as they ſay) certaine Statutes and Decrees made by their predeceſſors, to this effect, That any, be he Lay or Eccleſiaſtical, may not build Churches, Monaſteries, Hoſpitals and other places of piety and deuotion without ſpeciall permiſſion of the Seignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; they had againe ordeined in their Councell that the ſame ſhould take place in all places vnder their ſubiection, vpon paine to all tranſgreſſorſ of baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or perpetuall impriſonment, and confiſcation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21485:28"/>of the ground and ſale of the edifices. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſaid Duke and Senate the 26. of March 1605. following an other decree, made by the ſame Senate in the yeere 1536. by the which (as they affirme) it was expreſly forbidden, that any, vnder certaine pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties contained in the foreſaid decree, might net a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate in the ſame Citie and Duchie of Venice, nor leaue by will and teſtament, or donation betweene the liuing any goods immoueable, for pious and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious cauſes, nor bind ouer or pawne to ſuch intent, but only for a certaine time there expreſſed; a thing neuer before receiued or put in practiſe: had againe not only made the lame inhibition, but alſo expreſly prohited the alienations of the foreſaid immoueable goods made in fauour of the Eccleſiaſticall perſons without the permiſſion of the ſaid Senat: had more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer extended the foreſaid decree and penalties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained to all lands vnder their obedience, and had cauſed it to be publiſhed throughout all places and townes of their Seigniory: ordaining that all the foreſaid vnmoueable goods which were ſound to haue beene ſold or otherwaies aliened, beſides the paine of nullity, ſhould be confiſcate and ſold, and the price thereof diuided betweene the Magiſtrate execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the tenor of the foreſaid decree, his officers, and the informer and others, as hath beene reported vnto vs to be at large ſet out in the ſaid decree, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates of the ſaid Duke and Senate. Moreouer that the ſaid Duke and Senate had cauſed to be impriſoned Scipio Sarracino Canon of Vicenza, and Brandeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Valdemariuo of Fornoue Abbat of the Monaſtery or Abbey of Nerueſa in the Dioceſſe of Tarraſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21485:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21485:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21485:30"/>placed in dignity Eccleſiaſticke, and this for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine crimes, which are pretended to haue beene committed by them in the towne of Vicenza, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, vnder pretence that the conniſance thereof belonged vnto them, and that it is of their Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, grounding themſelues vpon certain priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges granted, (as they pretend) to the ſaid Duke and Senate, by certaine of our predeceſſours, Popes: wherein they preiudice the right of the Church, and impugne the liberty and immunity Eccleſiaſtical, and authority of the holy Sea Apoſtolike. And becauſe this turneth to the great ſcandale of the Church, and the perdition of the ſoules of the ſaid Duke and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: inſomuch as hauing dared to publiſh the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Decrees and Statutes, they haue thereby incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Eccleſiaſticall cenſures ordeined by the ſacred Canons of generall Councels, and by the decrees and conſtitutions of the Biſhops of Rome, and the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of goods &amp; lands which they hold of the Church, of the which penalties and cenſures they cannot bee abſolued nor diſcharged but by vs, or our ſucceſſour the Pope for the time being: and that moreouer they are vnable and vncapable to enioy the benefit of the foreſaid abſolution, vntill they haue actually reuoked the ſaid Statutes and Decrees by them publiſhed, and returned all againe that thereof hath enſued to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtate. For that alſo the ſaid Duke and Senate, after many fatherly admonitions, which to them haue beene made on our part, they haue made no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to reuoke the ſaid Decrees and Statutes, and that they ſtill keepe priſoners the ſaid Canon Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cino, and Abbat Brandelino, and that they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21485:30"/>no order to put them (as they ought) into the handes of our Nuntio, and of the holy Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
            <p>Wee, who muſt in no caſe ſuffer that the libertie and immunitie of the Church, and our authoritie, and of the holy Sea Apoſtolique be violated, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, following the Decrees of many generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and the examples of our predeceſſors, Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius the Third, Honorius the Third, Gregorie the Ninth, Alexander the Fourth, Clement the Fourth, Martin the Fourth, Boniface the Eight, Boniface the Ninth, Martin the Fift, Nicolas the Fift, and other Biſhops of Rome, which haue held this holy Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, ſome whereof haue reuoked the like ſtatures as void of themſelues, and declared them void, and of no force or vertue, being made againſt the libertie and immunitie of the Churche, and others haue yet gone further, euen to excommunicate the authors of ſuch ſtatutes and ordinances; hauing duely conſulted with our moſt venerable brethren the Cardinals of the holy Romane Church, with their counſell and conſent (albeit the ſaid decrees, edicts, and mandates be of themſelues void, &amp; of none effect) we haue not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding anew declared them void &amp; of no force and vertue, and being ſuch, declare that no man is bound to the obſeruation of them. And moreouer iſ the ſaid Duke and Senate within 24. daies (recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the day of the publication of theſe preſents in this Cittie, whereof we appoint vnto them eight daies for the firſt, eight for the ſecond, and the other eight for the third and laſt delay and for monition Canonicall) do not reuoke publiquely the foreſaid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21485:31"/>Decrees, and all that is therein conteined, and which is thereof inſued, laying aſide all excuſe and excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and do not caſhire and deface the Recordes and Regiſters, and places where they ſhall bee kept, and cauſe to be publiſhed by them, and publiquely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all the lands and territories vnder their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that no man is bound to the obſeruation of them, and do not returne al that is thereon enſued to it firſt eſtate; and if they do not promiſe, neuer more to enterpriſe to make the like Decrees and Statutes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the libertie, immunitie and iuriſdiction of the Church, againſt our authoritie, and the holy Sea A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique, and certifie vs of the ſaid reuocation, caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, reſtitution and promiſe; and if preſently they do not put the foreſaid Canon and Abbat into the handes of our ſaid Nuntio: In the authoritie of God Almightie, and of the thriſe-bleſſed Apoſtles, Saint Peter and Saint Paul, hauing for the preſent, and for heereafrer excommunicated, we pronounce and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare excommunicated the Duke and Senate of the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> which at this preſent are or heereafter ſhall be there, their fauourers, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers and adherents, and euerie one of them, albeit they be not named in theſe preſents, as well as if the names of them and euery one of them had there been ſpecially expreſſed; &amp; ſo that they can not obtain abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, nor be diſcharged of the ſaid ſentence of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication but only at point of death, &amp; by none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than our ſelf, or the Pope, for time being, without all poſſibility of helping themſelues by any facultie to them granted or to be granted in general, or to any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in particular. And if it happen that in extremity of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21485:31"/>death any of them be abſolued from the ſaid ſentence of Excommunication, who afterward recouers his health, hee ſhall thereupon fall againe into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me excommunication, vntill, as much as in him lieth, he hath obeyed. And neuertheleſſe, if hee die after the obtaining of the ſaid abſolution, that he be depriued of the buriall of the Church, till that our commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be obeyed. And if the foreſaid Duke and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate three daies after the foreſaid 24. daies be expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, harden their hearts (which God forbid) enduring the ſaid ſentence of excommunication, not obeying the ſame, for the preſent, as alſo for hereafter, we haue and do put to the Interdict of the Church the Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> and the other townes, burrowes, caſtles, ſeigniories, and all places whatſoeuer, and generally all the temporall demaines of the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; during which interdict, none may in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> the burrowes, Caſtles, and Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niories of the ſaid Common-wealth, ſay in the Churches and places of deuotion, oratories priuate, and houſhod Chappels, neither in publique, nor in priuate, any maſſes ſolemne, or not ſolemne, nor ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate diuine ſeruice; except in caſes to vs permitted and reſerued, and then only in the Churches, and no where elſe; as alſo the dores ſhut, without ſound of bell, and without the aſſiſtance of any the foreſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate and interdicted, and nor otherwiſe, whatſoeuer diſpenſations and priuiledges Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, which haue beene granted to any Churches as well ſecular as regular, and whatſoeuer exemptions that they haue, and that they are immediately ſubiect to the ſea Apoſtolique; and although they depend on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21485:32"/>the patronage or foundation &amp; dotation of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Duke and Senate, not in generall only, and vnder the name of the Common-wealth, but each one in particular of the Citizens and Subiects of the ſame, of all the fees, and goodes which they hold of the Church, vnder what title ſoeuer, and declare them depriued of the ſaid fees and goodes, and of all priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which haue beene granted and giuen vnto them by any of our Predeceſſors, as namely to take cogniſance of the crimes and defaults of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons. And neuertheleſſe if the ſaid Duke and Senate too opinatiue ſhall any longer harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their contumacie, wee reſerue eſpecially to our ſelues, and our ſucceſſors the Popes, the power to aggrauate, and reaggrauate the cenſures and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties Eccleſiaſticall againſt them and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and thoſe that ſhall any way aid, counſell, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet them, and to recouer them by other remedies in time conuenient, and to proceed againſt them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diſpoſition of the holy Canons: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any conſtitutions and ordinances Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique, priuiledges, diſpenſations, grants and other letters Apoſtolique in fauour of the ſaid Duke and Senate in generall, or any other perſons in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: Namely thoſe by vertue whereof they pretend that they cannot bee interdicted, ſuſpended, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, although the ſaid letters do not make expreſſe mention, word for word: and with Dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie of Derogatories, and other clauſes, as alſo all other Decrees, and ſpecially all faculties of abſoluing in caſes reſerued to vs, and the ſea Apoſtolique, and to them granted on the contrary by our predeceſſors,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21485:32"/>and approoued and confirmed by vs, and the holy ſea Apoſtolique; all which and euery one of them, wee haue repealed, and do repeale, and all things heereto contrarie. And to the end that theſe preſents may come to the knowledge of all, we appoint vnto you and to euery one of you moſt expreſly enioine and command, that by vertue of the holy obedience which you ow to the holy Sea, and apprehenſion of the laſt iudgement of interdict from the entrie of the Church, of ſuſpenſion of your charges, and perception of the fruits and reuenews of your houſes Patriarchall, Archiepiſcopall, Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, as much as to you belongeth our brethren the Patriarches, Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and of priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of dignities, offices, and benefices Eccleſiaſticall whatſoeuer by you poſſeſſed at this preſent, and in hability to poſſeſſe them heereafter; and foraſmuch as our Sonnes the Vicars and other forenamed, depend vpon you, that vpon paine of incurring the penalties which in caſe of diſobedience wee ſhall thinke ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and whereof you ſhall receiue theſe preſents, or that otherwiſe they ſhall come vnto your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; you by your ſelues, or others cauſe to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſolemnly, euery one in his Church, when there ſhall be greateſt number and concourſe of people: and cauſe theſe to be fixed and ſet vpon the doores of your Churches. And moreouer we will that in euery reſpect like credit be giuen to the doubles and copies of theſe in like manner printed, ſo be it they be ſigned with the hand of ſome publicke Notarie, &amp; ſealed with the ſeale of ſome perſons being in dignity Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, as to the originall it ſelfe, if it were exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21485:33"/>and ſhewed, and that theſe preſents, or the double and copie of them ſo printed, as hath beene ſaid, being affixed to the doores of the Church of Lateran, and palace of the Prince of the Apoſtles, and of our Chancery Apoſtolike, and publiſhed in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po de Flore, as it hath beene accuſtomed; haue as great force, againſt the foreſaid Duke and Senate, and all other, and you all in generall, and euery one reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely, as if they had beene perſonally addreſſed, intimated and preſented to euery one of them, and you. Giuen at Rome at S. Peters <hi>Sous l'aneau du peſcheur,</hi> the ſeuenteenth of April 1606. and the firſt yeare of our Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <trailer>M. Veſtrius Barbianus.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="protestation">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21485:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PROTESTATION OF the Duke and Senat of Venice <hi>againſt the Bull of Pope</hi> PAVL the Fift.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EONARD DONAT by the grace of God Duke of Venice, to the moſt Honourable Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, Priors, Rectors of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches, and other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Eccleſiaſticall throughout our Common wealth and Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory of Venice, Salutations. We are giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that by commandement of our moſt holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paul the Fift, a certaine Briefe hath beene thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and publiſhed at Rome the 17. of Aprill laſt paſt againſt our perſon, the Senat and Seigniory, and ſent to you to bee publiſhed in our townes and territories of our obedience and ſubiection. And becauſe wee who are bound to preſerue the tranquillity and peace of the State and gouernment to the which we are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined and appointed by God, and to maintaine the authority of our Common wealth, which beſides
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21485:34"/>the Maieſtie Diuine acknowledgeth no Superiour in matters Temporall: we proteſt by theſe preſents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and the whole world, that wee haue omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing of that which belonged to vs to make knowen to his holineſſe, the iuſtice and equitie of our lawes, as well by our Ambaſſador ordinary at Rome, and by letters, by the which wee haue ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the former Briefes to vs directed: as alſo by another Ambaſſadour extraordinarie ſent by vs of purpoſe for this buſineſſe. But hauing vnderſtood that his holineſſe hath from time to time ſet light by our remonſtrances, &amp; without giuing audience vnto our moſt iuſt reaſons hath decreed this briefe againſt all right, againſt that which holy Scripture, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the holy Fathers, &amp; ſacred Canons do teach, in preiudice of that power ſecular which God hath giuen into our hands, and of the libertie of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to the end to moleſt and trouble, not without great ſcandall, the life, the goods, and honors which our faithfull ſubiects do peaceably and quietly enioy vnder our authoritie: we make no doubt to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the ſaid Briefe as vnlawfull, and in it ſelfe void as well in fact and deed, as in law: and therfore haue thought it neceſſarie to take thoſe remedies, which our predeceſſors and other Princes of Chriſtendome haue vſed againſt the Popes, when they haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their power: aſſuring our ſelues that you, and other our faithfull ſubiects, and all the world will ſo iudge thereof: And as hitherto you haue diligently looked to the cure of the ſoules of our ſubiects, and carefully trauelled to keepe the ſeruice of God in his integritie, that heereafter you will continue in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21485:34"/>ſame dutie of true and good paſtors: conſidering that our intention is to perſiſt in the holie Catholique and Apoſtolique faith, and euermore to continue in the reuerence accuſtomed towards the holy Church of Rome: ſo we command you that you cauſe to be affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe preſents in the moſt open places of this town, and others of our obedience, to the end they may come to the knowledge of all our ſubiects, and of all thoſe that haue heard of the foreſaid briefe, ſo that it may come to the eares of our holy Father, whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding we deſire God by his holy Spirit ſo to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten, that he may ſee the nullitie of all that he hath done againſt vs, and that hauing vnderſtood the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equitie of our cauſe, he giue vs cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the obſeruance and reſpect which our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors and all the common-wealth haue hitherto rendred to the Sea Apoſtolique, whereto they haue alwaies ſhewed themſelues moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate. Giuen in our Pallace the 16. of May, Indiction the fourth the yeere of our Lord 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:21485:35"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21485:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>FATHER PAVLS Apologie for his not appearing <hi>at Rome, being called thither</hi> by citation.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To the right Honourable Lords, and moſt reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> Pinello, Aſcalano, S. Cecilie de Ciury, Blanchetto, Arigonio, Bellarmino, Sappata de Bubalis, Monopolitano, <hi>Cardinals of the moſt holy Church of Rome, named Inquiſitors Generall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble and Reuerend Lords:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Frier Paul, a Venetian, of the order of Seruants appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you by theſe letters, and moſt humbly and ſubmiſſiuely intreat that ye would (reuoking thoſe things that are inacted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee in your congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) daine to accept, and admit vnto due examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe my exceptions againſt them. For, about the twentieth day of September, it was decreed in your congregation, that a certaine booke compoſed by me in Italian thus intituled: <hi>Conſiderations vpon the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21485:36"/>cenſure of the holineſſe of Pope Paul the Fift againſt the renowmed Common wealth of Venice,</hi> ſhould not bee diuulged abroad, or read, or yet retained by any one which had it. Neither alſo one other booke intituled, <hi>An Apology for the oppoſitions of the renowmed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Lord Cardinall Bellarmine, to the treatiſes and reſolutions of Iohn Gerſon touching the validity of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</hi> Neither yet one other booke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by me, with ſixe other bearing this inſcription: <hi>A tractate of the interdict of the holineſſe of Pope Paul the Fift,</hi> with ſome other bookes of the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment compoſed by others, with all other which ſhould afterward be publiſhed of that argument, for that many things were found in them very raſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, <hi>calumnious, ſcandalous, ſeditious, ſciſmaticall, erroneous</hi> and <hi>hereticall reſpectiuely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, the thirtieth day of the moneth of October, a Citation was decreed againſt me, with Commandement that it ſhould bee hanged in the Court at Rome, with the penalty of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſentence being denounced againſt me, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of perpetuall infamie and depriuation from all and ſingular offices and dignities, and other penalties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the Canoicall conſtitutions and to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at your pleaſure, that I ſhould within the ſpace of twentie and foure dayes appeare in mine owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and not by a proctor, to giue an account of my faith, and to purge my ſelfe from all crimes obiected againſt me, for that it was obiected by and vnder the lawfull oath of men of credit, and manifeſt by other proofes, that there was no ſafe acceſſe to be made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, as it is reported to be conteined more fully and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21485:36"/>more at large in the foreſaid decrees and edicts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, to which &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Truely moſt Reuerend Lordes, I am readie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commandement of Saint Peter, to render an account of that faith and hope whereby I liue, to euerie one which demandeth it: and doe conſtantly affirm that a publique examination of our faith is moſt profitable and neceſſarie in the Church; to the intent that we may not be carried about with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie wind of doctrine, and that we may not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at vnawarres by them who vſe godlineſſe as a trade to gaine by. But as the vſe of this ſacred and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke is very ſoueraigne, ſo the abuſe of it is moſt peſtilent and pernitious, when vnder pretence thereof enuie is ſometimes ſtirred vp, contrarie to all diuine and humane lawes, and they which are not well bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are laden and oppreſſed with the hatred of others, and wholeſome doctrine is abandoned: by which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtruction of the Euangeliſts and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, both the world, and Common-wealths are gouerned, and do endure. Surely I wiſh and deſire nothing more, than to performe all ſubiection and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto you, and to render an account of my faith: neither do I flee the light, who being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Catholique faith (according to the Commandement of the Lord) haue giuen <hi>to Caeſar thoſe things which are Caeſars, and to God thoſe things which are Gods.</hi> But ſuch is the eſtate of times, and many things haue come to this paſſe, that all men may plainly ſee, that I am to be exempted from your citation and command.</p>
            <p>For when as without obſeruance of any lawfull
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21485:37"/>order, the bookes are interdicted and forbidden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the authors of them are heard to ſpeak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, neither any ſentences or propoſitions choſen out, marked and noted with ſpeciall cenſures, that it might be made manifeſt in euerie particular of what ſort they either were or might be eſteemed to be; as the cuſtome hath beene in former times, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obſerued in the Councell holden at Conſtance: but the matter deliuered after a new faſhion, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of, in an elaborate oration, namely that many things in thoſe bookes contained were very <hi>raſh, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious, ſcandalous, ſeditious, ſciſmaticall</hi> and <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall reſpectiuely;</hi> ſo that by reaſon of the obſcu the oration, and the vndetermined limitation of that aduerbe, it can not appeare, whether by all thoſe wordes, all the foreſaid bookes bee condemned, or what eſteeme we are to make of euerie one of them in particular, and this done to this end, that men might reſerue free libertie vnto themſelues to ſpeake when and what they would, as the occaſions of the future buſineſſe might moue them, and that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the bookes might haue their anſwers to ſeeke for the defending of their bookes. And ſince all bookes that might afterward be written of that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, which might containe in them the right and cauſe of the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie condemned, an end is put to any intended controuerſie in reſpect of any one which would be a publiſher or defender of their lawes and rights. Wherefore moſt renouned Lordes, ſince ſentence (though ambiguous and needing a manifold expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) is alreadie denounced againſt me concerning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21485:37"/>thoſe bookes which were compoſed by me, after ſo great a preiudice brought vpon mee, before I was heard ſpeak, it is not now lawful by any right, that any other iudgement ſhould be pronounced againſt me, as if the matter were intire, or that I ſhould be called to mine anſwer and cited to appeare after ſentence denounced againſt me.</p>
            <p>Neither beſides all this can I looke for vpright iudgement, when as (among the reſt) that worthy Lord <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> ſitteth as Iudge, who in a booke thus in Italian intituled <hi>An anſwer of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Bellarmine to a Treatiſe of ſeuen Diuines of Venice, concerning the Interdict of the holineſſe of our Lord Pope Paul the Fift, and to the oppoſitions of Friar Paul of the order of Seruants againſt the firſt writing of the ſaid Cardinall,</hi> doth plainly affirme that he had beene exceedingly iniured by the foreſaid Apologie, and wheras he doth not anſwer that which was obiected againſt him, hee heapeth vp a multitude of taunts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and on euerie ſide breatheth out reuenge, and therefore hee ought to haue abſteined from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing ſentence againſt me, or elſe from interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe as a iudge in this matter, either for feare of God or his owne conſcience terrifying him, or at leaſt for the auoiding of ſcandall.</p>
            <p>Furthermore this may bee added that ſentences and cenſures haue beene publiſhed againſt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Prince, the Senate, and Common wealth of Venice, and againſt their fauourers, adherents, and counſellers, whom I of duty and with bleſſing from the Reuerend Father Prior generall of my order of Seruants do ſerue in place of a Diuine &amp; an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21485:38"/>ciuill Lawyer; as others can not diſſemble their angrie minde againſt me, ſo I can not but be in great feare: which things ſeeing they be manifeſt to all men, needed not any longer diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing that (as it is auerred) it is manifeſt vnto you by the teſtimonie of men of credit and other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that there is no ſafe acceſſe vnto mee, to ſerue a perſonall citation, it ſhould bee farre more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant vnto the ſame men, that I ſhould haue farre leſſe ſafe, yea moſt dangerous paſſage vnto you: wherfore ye haue ſaued me a labour of prouing that which I purpoſed to haue done: for if ye being migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie men, bee not able to ſerue one citation on mee, ſhall I the meaneſt of all, being now abſent from the Communion of you and yours, looke for ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts, ſhall I haue ſafe acceſſe vnto you?</p>
            <p>Neither is this to bee laſt and leaſt regarded, that by the Edict of our renouned Prince, Eccleſiaſticall perſons are prohibited to depart out of this domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whom I ought in dutie eſpecially to obey both in regard of reſpects common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me with all others, as alſo for that the ſpirituall ſeruice being adioined with the regular and lawfull obedience vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, it is not only vnlawfull to depart out of the kingdome, but euen out of the Citie without leaue obtained.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelfe (Reuerend Lordes) I am readie to render an account of my faith vnto any man, and to anſwer any not ſuſpected Iudges: and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to take a iourney to any ſafe places.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the caſe thus ſtanding, I beſeech you, by the comming of that great and fearefull Iudge
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21485:38"/>(with whom there ſhall be no reſpect of perſons) that ye would not perſecute a worme, and dead dogge, but (as right requires) ye would admit of my exceptions, againſt the iudgements, the iudges, and the place of triall; and pronounce them iuſtly made. If yee doe otherwiſe, I pronounce a nullity in the ſight of God and his holy Church of your decrees, and all further proceedings; and commend my ſelfe to the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the almighty, and caſt the care of my ſelfe vpon his Maieſtie. And if I bee ſeparated from your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity (as you threaten to deale with mee) without all order of diuine or humane lawes, God aſſiſting me I am ready to beare it with a patient mind, being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine with Gelaſius, that <hi>an vniuſt ſentence can hurt no man, in the ſight of God and his Church.</hi> I am leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the threatned penalty of perpetuall infamie; I will ſpeake according to the ſaying of that moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man: Thinke of Auſten what you will, only let not my conſcience accuſe me in the ſight of God. S. Peter hath long ſince admoniſhed vs, that none ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as a man ſlaier, or a thiefe, or an euill ſpeaker, or a deſirer of other mens goods, but if hee ſuffereth as a Chriſtian let him not bee aſhamed. I ſhall excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly reioice with the holy Apoſtles, if I ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch for the doctrine of Chriſt, and the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul. But I am not aſhamed that I am defamed for expounding and defending the right of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, moſt mighty and renowmed Common wealth thorow the whole earth. I will alſo moſt willingly beare the infamie which I ſhall ſuffer for defending the memory and credit of Iohn Gerſon, a moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctor, and a man of admirable learning and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21485:39"/>pietie, and exceeding good deſert of the Church of Rome: Truſting that through the puritie of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall and Apoſtolicall doctrine, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of ſo great a Common-wealth, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne and fame of that moſt holy Doctor, the mark of vniuſt and vndeſerued infamy ſhall be taken away. I nothing reſpect the puniſhment of being depriued from offices and dignities which yee threaten beſide excommunication: I neither deſire any offices or dignities, neither would I receiue any if they were offered. I am fully determined to applie my ſelfe to the ſeruice of God in that calling in which hee hath placed me. Let thoſe bee moued with ſuch ſcarre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowes, who do account them puniſhments. I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it an eſpeciall office and dignitie to liue all my life in this moſt baſe and low degree.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time ſince I can not come vnto you to render by liuely voice an account of my faith for reaſons aboue mentioned, and others in their due place and time to be alledged: by my works alreadie publiſhed, and thoſe which I ſhall heereafter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, I haue and will render you a full account of it, and I will keepe entire that dutie, obedience, and faith, which I haue heeretofore borne towards you, (eſpecially ſo many yeeres as I was conuerſant at Rome) hoping that God will giue me opportunitie, time, and occaſion to approue my innocencie vnto you, and the whole world, and heare mee in his due time, and in the meane while giue mee ſuch ſucceſſe with my tentation, that I ſhall be able to beare it. But I do earneſtly intreat and beſeech you by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt our Lord, and your dutie and place
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21485:39"/>in the Church of God, if ye haue thought any ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and propoſitions in my writing worthie repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, (ſince it can not bee coniectured from the doubtfull wordes of the former edict, what they are) that yee would command that they bee ſelected out, and noted with fit markes, that I, agreeing to your iudgement, to which I will alwaies attribute much, may either expound them if they bee not cleere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, or elſe fortifie them with more ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and arguments. For in the meane time whileſt they are condemned together with other writings of other men without any ſpeciall exception, <hi>with an amhiguous aduerb,</hi> I proteſt that there can be nothing found in them worthy reprehenſion. <hi>At Venice from the Conuent of Seruants. Nouember</hi> 29. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
